<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.2" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>VORSITZ: EVELYN REGNER </em> <br /> <em>Vizepräsidentin</em> </p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.3" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="09:00:00" url="">Opening of the sitting</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.5" nospeaker="true" time="09:02:10" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>(Die Sitzung wird um 9.02 Uhr eröffnet.)</em> </p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.6" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="09:02:10" url="">Establishing the Digital Decade Policy Programme 2030 (debate)</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.8" speakername="Evelyn Regner" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9145" time="09:02:20" url=""><p lang='de'>Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über den Bericht von Martina Dlabajová im Namen des Ausschusses für Industrie, Forschung und Energie über den Vorschlag für einen Beschluss des Europäischen Parlaments und des Rates über das Politikprogramm für 2030 „Weg in die digitale Dekade“ (<a href="#reds:iEcCom/COM-2021-0574" data-rel="reds" redmap-uri="/reds:iEcCom/COM-2021-0574">COM(2021)0574</a> – C9-0359/2021 – <a href="#reds:DirContProc/COD-2021-0293" data-rel="reds" redmap-uri="/reds:DirContProc/COD-2021-0293">2021/0293(COD)</a>) ( <a href="#reds:iPlRp/A-9-2022-0159" data-rel="reds" redmap-uri="/reds:iPlRp/A-9-2022-0159">A9-0159/2022</a>). </p></speech>
        <speech lang="cs" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.10" speakername="Martina Dlabajová" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7939" time="09:02:34" url=""><p lang='cs'> <em>rapporteur</em> <em>.</em> – Mr Commissioner, I am speaking in Czech.</p><p lang='cs'> – Paní předsedající, cloudové služby, <em>big data</em>, umělá inteligence, veřejné služby online, digitální identifikace, přístup ke zdravotnickým dokumentům odkudkoliv nebo běžně využívané elektronické faktury, to není sci-fi, to musí být velmi brzy realita nás všech. Evropa má šanci dnes úspěšně vykročit na cestu, která nás do konce dekády dovede k plné digitální transformaci naší ekonomiky i společnosti. Do doby, kdy občané a firmy budou plně využívat výhody, které nabízí digitalizace a které přináší používání nových moderních technologií. </p><p lang='cs'>Politický program „Cesta k digitální dekádě“ na rok 2030 nevymýšlí nic nového, ale nakládá s tím, co už je. Vychází z předpokladu, že samotné státy chtějí neustále pracovat na zlepšování a chtějí vzájemně spolupracovat a posouvat se společně dál. Cíle digitalizace, se kterými digitální dekáda počítá, prošly konzultacemi se členskými státy a já věřím, že i proto jsou reálné a splnitelné. Osobně jsem dbala na to, aby se do konzultací zapojili také zástupci podniků, a to nejen těch velkých, ale i malých a středních a start-upů. Často jsou to právě malé a střední firmy, které jsou průkopníky v nějaké oblasti, a ostatní od nich nová řešení přebírají nebo v nich hledají inspiraci. Co považuji za největší úspěch našich jednání a výsledného kompromisu? Digitální dekáda přichází s šikovným návodem, jak co nejlépe a nejefektivněji zkombinovat investice z rozpočtu EU, včetně Nástroje pro obnovu a odolnost, investice z členských států a také ze soukromého sektoru. Synergie jsou pak alfou a omegou úspěšnosti a přidané hodnoty. Díky politickému programu digitální dekáda můžeme lépe vyrovnávat rozdíly mezi členskými státy v oblastech, kde je to nejvíce potřeba. A v neposlední řadě se otevíráme možnostem mezinárodní spolupráce. Avšak za jasně narýsovaných podmínek a podle dohodnutých pravidel na hřišti vykolíkovaném programy, které ji financují. </p><p lang='cs'>A bez čeho se neobejdeme? Za prvé je to konektivita. Bez zajištění připojení, které pořád není po celé Evropě samozřejmostí, nezmůžeme nic a můžeme jít hned teď všichni domů. Zabezpečená a udržitelná digitální infrastruktura je naprostý základ. Včerejší den, kdy se Evropský parlament stal terčem kybernetického útoku, je toho názornou ukázkou. Za druhé, neobejdeme se bez digitálních dovedností, a to nejen těch základních, které by do konce roku 2030 mělo mít minimálně 80 % populace. Firmám a také státní správě např. stále chybí lidé, kteří by dokázali školit a předávat své know-how dál. Postrádám také motivaci pro ty, co už na trhu práce jsou, aby se učili novým dovednostem a dále se rozvíjeli. O dlouholetém zoufalém volání pracovního trhu po specialistech v informačních a komunikačních technologiích ani nemluvím. Za třetí potřebujeme digitalizované služby veřejné správy. Pokud opravdu chceme, aby občané a firmy pokládali digitalizaci za přínos a viděli v ní příležitosti, musíme jít příkladem. Digitalizace státu, přístup ke klíčovým veřejným službám online, elektronické zdravotnictví a mohla bych pokračovat – to nesmí zůstávat na papíře a doslova v papírové formě. A konečně digitální transformace podniků. Téma, kterým bychom mohli zaplnit agendu celého plenárního zasedání, a ještě by to nestačilo. Digitalizace musí podnikům velkým i malým otevírat cestu k lepšímu podnikání. A nesmí je v žádném případě neúměrně zatěžovat a demotivovat. Věřím, že to zvládneme. A jak už jsem řekla, pokud dnes digitální dekádu schválíme, první krok na cestě k ní jsme už udělali.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.12" speakername="Thierry Breton" speakerid="unknown" time="09:07:04" url=""><p lang='fr'> <em>membre de la Commission</em> <em>.</em> – Madame la Présidente, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, tout d’abord, je voudrais remercier chaleureusement Mme la rapporteure, Martina Dlabajová, chère Martina, et toute l’équipe de rapporteurs fictifs qui ont travaillé sans relâche et en un laps de temps extrêmement court afin de finaliser dans un temps record cette proposition. Alors grâce à ce texte, comme cela vient d’être rappelé par la rapporteure, nous allons donner à l’Europe les moyens d’organiser une transformation numérique ambitieuse.</p><p lang='fr'>Ces trois dernières années, face à l’ensemble des défis que nous avons eu à gérer – et on sait qu’on en aura encore beaucoup à gérer devant nous –, nous avons pu voir les possibilités réelles offertes par l’ensemble des technologies numériques pour toute notre économie, nos économies et d’une façon plus générale pour la société. Et nous avons mis en place une relance économique également, je vous le rappelle, fortement basée sur la transformation numérique.</p><p lang='fr'>Le programme d’action pour la décennie numérique est évidemment la vision, la pierre angulaire de cette transformation. Pour la première fois, en effet, nous fixons au niveau européen des objectifs concrets, quantitatifs et mesurables. C’est très important pour nous permettre d’atteindre ce que nous devons réaliser d’ici à 2030 dans le domaine du numérique, car il n’y a pas de décennies numériques ni d’Europe résiliente sans l’excellence de nos ingénieurs, sans une meilleure connectivité partout en Europe, sans que les PME possèdent elles aussi toutes les infrastructures nécessaires, sans processeurs compétitifs et durables – et de plus en plus, on le souhaite, fabriqués sur le continent européen.</p><p lang='fr'>Nous voulons que l’Europe soit un continent pleinement connecté, doté d’infrastructures nécessaires, capables de stocker, de transmettre, de traiter de très vastes domaines, de gigantesques volumes de données, et qui permettent par la suite d’autres évolutions technologiques. Et c’est la raison pour laquelle nous avons fixé des objectifs très concrets pour la fibre optique, la 5G, le <em>cloud</em>, le quantique, qui est aussi très important, la microélectronique, etc.</p><p lang='fr'>Les entreprises qui maîtrisent les technologies numériques sont celles qui résistent le mieux à la crise. On le voit tous les jours. C’est donc pour être plus résilient que, d’ici à 2030, nous voulons que 90 % de nos PME accroissent leur capacité en termes de technologies numériques.</p><p lang='fr'>Une société formée à l’ère du numérique est aussi nécessaire pour que nos entreprises soient propulsées par des femmes et des hommes de talents. Notre objectif dans ce domaine est de renforcer très sensiblement les compétences numériques de l’ensemble de nos concitoyens européens et de disposer aussi de 20 millions d’ingénieurs spécialisés dans le numérique en Europe d’ici à 2030. Et je dis que c’est un objectif très ambitieux dans lequel les femmes doivent prendre toute leur place. Il y a vraiment un très grand avenir pour elles dans ce domaine et nous devons les aider à y parvenir.</p><p lang='fr'>Nous avons également pour objectif de garantir l’accès à des services publics modernes, numériques et de haute qualité dans l’ensemble de l’Union européenne. En effet, il ne s’agit pas de se fixer des objectifs, encore faut-il se donner les moyens de les atteindre. Et c’est tout l’enjeu du processus structuré, du suivi de gouvernance que nous mettons en place. Il va nous permettre de progresser ensemble et sans délai en engageant l’intégralité des États membres. C’est pourquoi le programme d’action comprend une gouvernance solide, transparente, mais aussi, dans le même temps, assez souple pour pouvoir suivre les objectifs et nous adapter. Et pour cela, on va s’appuyer sur l’expérience acquise, notamment dans le cadre des plans nationaux pour la reprise et la résilience et, évidemment, en coordination avec le Semestre européen.</p><p lang='fr'>En conclusion, je voudrais dire que le programme d’action comprend également un cadre pour l’élaboration et la mise en œuvre de projets multi-pays, c’est-à-dire de projets à grande échelle visant à réaliser la transformation numérique de l’Union et les objectifs également très importants de relance industrielle. On le sait, dans ce domaine comme dans bien d’autres, aucun pays ne peut désormais y parvenir seul.</p><p lang='fr'>C’est pour cela que nous nous dotons d’un nouvel outil, le Consortium pour une infrastructure numérique européenne, dit EDIC, et ce mécanisme facilitera la mise en commun des ressources des États membres, du budget de l’Union et des investissements privés. Il permettra ainsi de déployer et de gérer des infrastructures paneuropéennes de manière efficace, par exemple les espaces européens de données ou des infrastructures de <em>blockchain</em>. Et de notre côté, je tiens à vous le redire ici, Mesdames et Messieurs les parlementaires, la Commission est prête à réagir très vite, dès l’adoption de cette décision, pour soutenir les projets de consortium matures. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.14" speakername="Sabine Verheyen" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7407" time="09:12:41" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Verfasserin der Stellungnahme des mitberatenden Ausschusses für Kultur und Bildung</em> <em>.</em> – Frau Präsidentin, sehr geehrter Herr Kommissar! Die Europäische Union darf sich bei der Digitalisierung nicht abhängen lassen. Der Aufbruch Europas in die digitale Dekade ist überfällig, wenn wir global mithalten wollen. Doch alle technischen Fortschritte, die wir machen, bedeuten nichts, wenn wir die Menschen nicht dafür bereitmachen und sie mitnehmen. <em>Digital literacy</em> wird in der Zukunft zu den wichtigsten Fähigkeiten gehören, die wir beherrschen sollten. Ich bin der festen Überzeugung, dass dies ein entscheidender Faktor für den Arbeitsmarkt sein wird.</p><p lang='de'>Doch um das bei möglichst vielen Menschen zu erreichen, gilt ein Grundsatz: <em>First teach the teachers</em>. Zunächst brauchen wir ausgebildetes Personal, das das Wissen weitergeben kann, sonst kann uns eine grundlegende Digitalisierung der Bevölkerung nicht gelingen. Das betrifft das Lehrpersonal in Schulen, aber auch vor allem im Bereich der Weiterbildung. Wir dürfen bei der Digitalisierung niemanden zurücklassen – egal welche Altersklasse, egal welche soziale Schicht. Meiner Meinung nach müssen wir dabei drei Punkte erfüllen, um erfolgreich zu sein: Wir müssen Lehrpersonal weiterbilden, wir müssen das lebenslange Lernen fördern und die nötige digitale Infrastruktur in Schulen und Bildungseinrichtungen schaffen.</p><p lang='de'>Einige Länder der EU sind bereits deutlich weiter fortgeschritten bei der Digitalisierung als andere. Aber wie sagt man im Sport so schön: Wir sind nur so stark wie unser schwächstes Mitglied. Packen wir es also gemeinsam an und bringen Europa in die digitale Dekade! Nutzen wir die Zeit jetzt, um die notwendigen Investments in Menschen und Infrastruktur zu schaffen!</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.16" speakername="Dragoş Pîslaru" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9934" time="09:14:27" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>rapporteur for the opinion of the Committee on Employment and Social Affairs</em> <em>.</em> – Madam President, Commissioner Breton, dear colleagues, congratulations to the rapporteur Martina Dlabajová for the great job on this file. I will begin by saying something that I firmly believe: Europe in the future will be digital or it won’t work at all. There are risks since the dawn of time with all new technologies but, harnessed properly, digitalisation can lead to more access and opportunity for those often left behind, not just for companies and tech giants. We can also use inclusive technologies to integrate people with disabilities. AI can avoid previous human biases in recruitment and, with the right digital skills, more people will gain access to new social prospects. But this will not happen by itself. We have to ensure that digitalisation leaves no one behind, nor is it used to create gaps in our legislation or to exploit workers or curtail their rights. Happy workers mean happy companies. So let’s use the Digital Decade to make that happen in Europe.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="sk" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.18" speakername="Ivan Štefanec" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8335" time="09:15:45" url=""><p lang='sk'> <em>za skupinu PPE</em> <em>.</em> – Vážená pani predsedajúca, od úrovne digitalizácie závisí úspech ekonomickej úrovne celej Únie aj úroveň života našich občanov. </p><p lang='sk'>Z môjho pohľadu sú dôležité tri oblasti. Po prvé, je to úroveň infraštruktúry. Musíme viac investovať do digitálnej infraštruktúry. Musíme motivovať súkromných investorov, aby investovali do digitálnej infraštruktúry, a od toho súvisí aj naša legislatívna práca, aby sme motivovali čo najviac pre lepšie investície, pre lepšiu dostupnosť internetu. Preto, aby pre občanov a firmy bol internet dostupnejší a cenovo prístupnejší. </p><p lang='sk'>Po druhé, je to legislatívna úroveň. V tomto Parlamente sme prijali mnohé zákony a je dobré, že nastavujeme celosvetové štandardy digitálnej legislatíve. No a po tretie, je to úroveň zručností. Musíme viac a viac investovať do digitálnych zručností aj z európskych peňazí. Dôležitou témou sú takisto malé podniky, ktoré zamestnávajú najviac pracovníkov, a ich úroveň digitalizácie takisto bude determinovať náš úspech. </p><p lang='sk'>Verím, že tie ambiciózne ciele, aby do roku 2030 sme mali všetky dokumenty online v styku s verejnou správou, v styku s verejnými inštitúciami, aby všetky zdravotné záznamy boli online, sú splniteľné, a verím, že úrovňou digitalizácie posunieme aj životnú úroveň občanov. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.20" speakername="Josianne Cutajar" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9688" time="09:17:20" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>on behalf of the S&amp;D Group</em> <em>.</em> – Madam President, the EU is finally taking a tangible commitment towards digitalisation through important trajectories and targets.</p><p lang='en'>The digital decade we’ve negotiated with the Council gives Member States enough flexibility to pursue digitalisation whilst taking into account their different starting points. Yet digitalisation is not an end in itself, but a means to broader societal outcomes. We have committed to achieving reliable, fast and secure connectivity for everywhere in the Union, including in rural and remote areas such as islands. By 2030, 80% of those aged 16 to 74 should have basic digital skills. There are targets for our SMEs and targets when it comes to big data and AI. A fast and steady creation of digital skills is essential if we want to also address cybersecurity concerns. In this regard, it’s very important that we continue working together.</p><p lang='en'>Until then, however, let’s keep in mind the disadvantaged, our elderly who cannot access the internet and let’s maintain offline accessibility of public services whilst we transit. Whilst the new measures will encourage social inclusion, democratisation of digital skills, narrowing the gender gap, our fight towards a just digital market should continue and our strive towards this. And in this regard, we should agree and work towards stronger digital rights, including access to the internet as a fundamental right.</p><p lang='en'>Let’s ensure that the Europe of 2030 will be digitally ready, fully connected, leading ahead whilst leaving no one behind.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="ro" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.22" speakername="Vlad-Marius Botoş" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9638" time="09:19:21" url=""><p lang='ro'> <em>în numele grupului Renew</em> <em>.</em> – Doamnă președintă, domnule comisar Breton, doamnă Martina Dlabajová, stimați colegi, fie că ne place sau nu, întreaga lume trece rapid într o eră digitală. Însă această digitalizare accelerată trebuie să pună în centrul ei interesul cetățeanului.</p><p lang='ro'>Succesul sau insuccesul nostru ca societate, ca uniune va depinde de câteva aspecte deosebit de importante. Va trebui să stimulăm domeniul digital, companiile implicate în digitalizare și să dăm posibilitatea specialiștilor să-și dezvolte ideile aici, în Uniunea Europeană. Va fi absolută nevoie de programe și proiecte care să învețe cetățenii să utilizeze instrumentele digitale, să creeze și să trăiască într un mediu digital. Nu în ultimul rând, trebuie să ținem cont că această digitalizare trebuie să ușureze munca și viața oamenilor.</p><p lang='ro'>Nu facem digitalizarea de dragul digitalizării, ci o facem în beneficiul oamenilor. Toate acestea însă vor putea fi făcute doar dacă vom avea o abordare europeană la nivel de Uniune, pentru a ne asigura că drepturile tuturor cetățenilor europeni sunt respectate, că toți avem aceleași șanse, indiferent în ce regiune trăim, că nimeni nu este lăsat în urmă.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.24" speakername="Jordi Solé" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7593" time="09:20:52" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group</em> <em>.</em> – Madam President, Mr Commissioner, rapporteurs, shadow rapporteurs, colleagues, during this decade, we want to give the EU’s digital transition a decisive boost. We had the Compass and now, with today’s decision, we have the concrete targets that we as a Union need to achieve by 2030 and the way to get there. Now all we need to do is to add political will and financial resources to these tools.</p><p lang='en'>In the digitalisation of the economy and society, much is at stake. We have to avoid lagging behind in terms of competitiveness for our economy and companies. We strive to be able to compete for leadership positions in the field of ICT and other advanced technologies. Issues such as territorial balance, technological sovereignty, the efficiency of public services and administration, energy sustainability or social cohesion are also at stake.</p><p lang='en'>Incorporation into the digital world should not result in more fractures and divides in our societies. This is why it is so important that the targets that we have agreed upon produce positive effects in each and every of these areas. </p><p lang='en'>On the positive balance of the final outcome, I want to emphasise the fact that we included the regional dimension in the digital transition. There are sub-state governments, like the Catalan government, that are very active in digital policies, and it’s good that they become involved with the joint endeavour to reach the 2030 targets.</p><p lang='en'>On the negative side, I regret that governments didn’t accept even the possibility for the Commission to issue recommendations to those Member States not on track with digital benchmarks. That no doubt would have helped the implementation of the targets. </p><p lang='en'>It’s also regrettable that we couldn’t fully counter the big push from some big Member States to introduce in the final text a reference, albeit indirectly, to the so-called fair share principle for investments in digital infrastructures. We need to ensure that net neutrality rules will not be changed and consumers and businesses will not have to pay more for online services due to a misleading concept of fair share. But this is a story to be continued. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="it" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.26" speakername="Elena Lizzi" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9856" time="09:23:33" url=""><p lang='it'> <em>a nome del gruppo ID</em> <em>.</em> – Signora Presidente, signor Commissario, on. Dlabajová, onorevoli colleghi, per prima cosa vorrei ringraziare la collega Dlabajová per la proficua collaborazione e per avere anche accolto i nostri contributi.</p><p lang='it'>Questa decisione stabilisce obiettivi digitali concreti che l'Unione europea intende raggiungere entro la fine del decennio, come è stato detto, e noi abbiamo ritenuto che si vada nella giusta direzione. Abbiamo però inserito ed evidenziato il problema del <em>reskilling</em> perché bisogna trovare i finanziamenti per digitalizzare le persone over 50 che non hanno dimestichezza con questi nuovi strumenti e che devono aggiornarsi per fronteggiare le nuove esigenze. Queste generazioni possiedono un ampio know-how, ricchezza di informazioni e contenuti e possono sostenere con l'esperienza le nuove leve, che avranno le competenze informatiche digitali.</p><p lang='it'>L'incontro intergenerazionale deve essere inclusivo affinché tutti traggano vantaggio e anche per raggiungere l'obiettivo di avere i 20 milioni di specialisti impiegati nel settore delle tecnologie dell'informazione e della comunicazione. Così l'Unione europea deve ricorrere all'utilizzo di tutti i programmi, soprattutto della ricerca, come per esempio creare un legame più forte con l'EIT e con la KIC Digital.</p><p lang='it'>Bene l'attenzione prestata alle piccole e medie imprese, bisogna dedicare loro tutta la nostra attenzione per evitare che il nostro tessuto economico e sociale si deteriori. Le nostre aziende devono essere supportate nel processo di transizione con corsi e finanziamenti mirati e di questo si deve occupare la politica europea.</p><p lang='it'>Poi ci è piaciuto che la Commissione svilupperà insieme agli Stati membri traiettorie a livello europeo per ciascuno degli obiettivi digitali dell'Unione europea e, a loro volta, gli Stati membri dovranno impegnarsi a sviluppare le traiettorie e le tabelle di marcia strategiche nazionali per raggiungere questi obiettivi, che devono essere chiari e sostenibili.</p><p lang='it'>Inoltre, il concetto di progetti multinazionali faciliterà gli investimenti in settori quali il calcolo ad alte prestazioni, le infrastrutture e i servizi di dati comuni, la blockchain, il partenariato ad alta tecnologia per le competenze digitali e le infrastrutture quantistiche sicure, nonché la rete di centri di sicurezza informatica, la pubblica amministrazione digitale, le strutture di prova e i cluster di innovazione digitale.</p><p lang='it'>Molte aziende e industrie italiane sono interessate a questi progetti infrastrutturali e speriamo che il nostro voto favorevole serva da propulsore per il raggiungimento degli obiettivi stabiliti.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="sv" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.28" speakername="Johan Nissinen" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10161" time="09:26:29" url=""><p lang='sv'> <em>för ECR-gruppen</em> <em>.</em> – Fru talman! EU har blivit världsmästare på att reglera digitaliseringen, i stället för att stödja innovation och nytänkande. Vi har därför halkat efter på global nivå. Jag stöder idén att satsa på digital utveckling, eftersom det är någonting bra, men jag fruktar att denna strategi kommer att misslyckas. Jag hoppas att jag har fel. Den innehåller många vackra ord och otroligt ambitiösa mål, i stället för en effektiv strategi som kommer ge valuta för våra pengar. Det är genom ekonomiska reformer och utbildning som vi skapar varaktig utveckling för framtiden och inte genom ineffektiv byråkrati som ger upphov till slöseri.</p><p lang='sv'>Trots att EU spenderar mer pengar än både USA och Asien på digitaliseringen, ligger vi fortfarande efter. Detta är inte rimligt. Vi kan inte fortsätta i samma hjulspår, utan vi måste börja tänka nytt.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="pt" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.30" speakername="Sandra Pereira" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9922" time="09:27:40" url=""><p lang='pt'> <em>em nome do Grupo The Left</em> <em>.</em> – Senhora Presidente, as tecnologias digitais têm o potencial de melhorar o acesso dos cidadãos à informação e à cultura, bem como proporcionar-lhes uma escolha mais vasta, diversificada e fácil no acesso a bens e serviços públicos e potenciar a sua qualidade de vida. </p><p lang='pt'>Mas este guião para a década digital segue a cartilha neoliberal das instituições europeias, orientado para o mercado único digital, que tem sido um instrumento promotor de desigualdades entre Estados-Membros, dificultando, particularmente, a vida das micro, pequenas e médias empresas, que não conseguem fazer face à concorrência e à brutal desigualdade dos meios e dos recursos que estão ao alcance das grandes empresas multinacionais do setor, e agora também dos já institucionalizados unicórnios. </p><p lang='pt'>De acordo com a proposta, os Estados-Membros deverão elaborar roteiros nacionais subordinados às recomendações específicas por país, formuladas no âmbito do Semestre Europeu, a que nos opomos por ser parte integrante dos instrumentos de imposição, condicionamento e controlo da União Europeia sobre as políticas dos Estados-Membros.</p><p lang='pt'>A realidade mostra que o guião deveria já ser outro. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="pt" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.32" speakername="Maria da Graça Carvalho" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/5347" time="09:29:01" url=""><p lang='pt'> – Senhora Presidente, Caro Comissário, caros Colegas, cara Relatora Martina Dlabajová, a transição digital é um dos pilares da estratégia da União Europeia para a próxima década. Do seu sucesso dependerá, em muito, a competitividade da nossa economia. Esta é uma corrida para a qual partimos com atraso, face a alguns países, como os Estados Unidos. </p><p lang='pt'>Para recuperarmos terreno temos de investir fortemente nas infraestruturas, na modernização das empresas, indústrias e serviços públicos, na economia dos dados, num forte mercado interno digital, na educação e formação, tanto nos quadros como na população em geral, na investigação científica e inovação. </p><p lang='pt'>A afirmação da União Europeia passará pela aposta em tecnologias emergentes como a computação quântica. Temos de ser capazes de criar as condições para que estas tecnologias se desenvolvam e sejam produzidas na Europa. </p><p lang='pt'>Um bom exemplo do rumo a seguir são as parcerias do Programa-Quadro Horizonte Europa, abrangendo temas como as tecnologias digitais essenciais e os circuitos integrados, a computação de alto desempenho e as redes 5G e 6G.</p><p lang='pt'>Este guião para a década digital, com os seus objetivos ambiciosos, só será concretizado se reunirmos todas estas condições. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="es" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.34" speakername="Lina Gálvez Muñoz" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9740" time="09:30:56" url=""><p lang='es'> – Señora presidenta, comisario, la digitalización abre muchísimas oportunidades para las y los europeos, también para sus territorios, pero también puede generar exclusiones y acrecentar desigualdades que sin duda tenemos que combatir desde las políticas públicas y también con una mayor participación democrática. Este itinerario para la década digital 2030 tiene el objetivo de fortalecer la soberanía digital europea, que sin duda es un elemento esencial para garantizar nuestra resiliencia y también nuestra autonomía estratégica.</p><p lang='es'>Me congratula especialmente ver recogidos en el acuerdo final la necesidad de garantizar las habilidades digitales básicas y un aumento de esos objetivos para el 80 % de las personas, y permitir así a la ciudadanía tener las habilidades básicas necesarias para participar plenamente en la sociedad digital y alcanzar finalmente la alfabetización digital amplia.</p><p lang='es'>Especialmente me congratula, y ha sido un esfuerzo muy grande de nuestro grupo, los socialistas y demócratas, que haya medidas específicas de apoyo para superar el grave desequilibrio de género, ya que solo una de cada seis especialistas en tecnología de la información y la comunicación, y solo una de cada tres graduadas en STEM, es decir en ciencia, tecnología, ingeniería y matemáticas, son mujeres.</p><p lang='es'>Y, finalmente, también la variable regional, ya que ninguna región se puede quedar atrás de este progreso digital.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.36" speakername="Valérie Hayer" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9785" time="09:32:32" url=""><p lang='fr'> – Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, aujourd’hui, pour la première fois, nous définissons des étapes claires pour collectivement faire de notre ambition numérique européenne une réalité. Cette ambition, c’est celle d’un monde numérique construit autour de l’humain, qui respecte les droits fondamentaux. Un monde innovant, accessible à tous. Un monde qui s’appuie sur des compétences renforcées sur l’ensemble du territoire européen. </p><p lang='fr'>Mes chers collègues, si nous voulons faire de cette révolution numérique une réussite, il nous faudra répondre à deux impératifs. </p><p lang='fr'>Premier impératif: la numérisation de nos sociétés doit aller de pair avec nos engagements climatiques. Nous avons besoin d’infrastructures durables et d’un numérique plus vert. Mais nous avons aussi besoin de développer les technologies numériques qui permettront de réduire nos émissions dans l’agriculture, dans l’énergie ou encore dans le transport. </p><p lang='fr'>Deuxième impératif: nous aurons besoin – nous le savons – d’investissements conséquents si nous voulons atteindre nos objectifs pour 2030. Cet effort devrait être porté de façon juste entre les principaux acteurs numériques concernés. C’est un point important. La déclaration européenne sur les droits et principes numériques pour la décennie numérique le précise. Nous aurons l’occasion d’en débattre très largement.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.38" speakername="David Cormand" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9685" time="09:33:47" url=""><p lang='fr'> – Madame la Présidente, merci à la rapporteure, merci, Monsieur le Commissaire, d’être ici avec nous. Il y a un angle mort dans ce texte: pour moi, c’est la question durable et c’est la question verte. La décennie numérique, ça nous emmène à 2030. On a des objectifs climatiques d’ici 2030. Et dans ce texte, il n’y a rien qui encadre ce que nous décidons de mettre en œuvre comme infrastructure pour pouvoir remplir ces objectifs.</p><p lang='fr'>Quand on parle de développement du numérique, il y a une question qu’on ne pose pas. Pourtant, quand on veut définir des critères sociaux et des critères environnementaux, on fait des études d’impact. Ici, pour le numérique, les études d’impact sont facultatives.</p><p lang='fr'>La question du numérique, c’est une question d’infrastructures. Ces infrastructures, elles entraînent des usages. Toute stratégie cohérente pour une puissance économique comme la nôtre devrait être conditionnée par la question de savoir quels sont les véritables besoins. On décrète dans ce texte qu’il faudrait que 90 % des PME soient intensives en numérique. Pourquoi? D’où sortent ces chiffres? Pourquoi on n’a pas une analyse plus sobre, plus résiliente de la conception du numérique?</p><p lang='fr'>Je veux dire que dans le monde dans lequel nous sommes, l’Union européenne doit être une puissance politique de stratégie et de stabilisation. Aujourd’hui, il y a deux modèles numériques dominants dans le monde: celui de la Chine – on ne veut évidemment pas y ressembler – et celui des GAFAM américains – et je pense que nous ne devons pas non plus leur ressembler. Quel est l’alter-modèle européen en la matière? Depuis le début, on nous dit que le numérique est naturellement l’allié de la transition écologique. Toutes les études, toutes les études qui existent sur l’impact écologique du numérique démontrent précisément le contraire. Je souhaite que nous fassions preuve de lucidité par rapport à ce domaine. Toute technologie n’est pas bonne, forcément, en soi. C’est le pouvoir politique qui décide de faire en sorte qu’une innovation technologique est au service du bien commun. Je souhaite que dans les semaines, dans les mois et dans les années qui viennent, notre institution veille à ce que ce soit le cas pour le numérique. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="it" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.40" speakername="Matteo Adinolfi" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9567" time="09:36:12" url=""><p lang='it'> – Signora Presidente, onorevoli colleghi, la pandemia ha messo in luce la necessità di una maggiore digitalizzazione della nostra economia e della nostra società.</p><p lang='it'>La trasformazione digitale ci offre infatti una grande possibilità per creare nuove opportunità per i giovani europei e migliorare l'accessibilità alle competenze digitali e renderle più fruibili a tutti i cittadini. Accrescere le competenze digitali dei cittadini europei, che sono in una situazione di ritardo sostanziale rispetto agli altri paesi industrializzati, è di fondamentale importanza.</p><p lang='it'>Ciò passa attraverso il potenziamento dell'infrastruttura digitale, che deve essere portata ai massimi standard per garantire competitività e sicurezza. In quest'ottica, la produzione europea di semiconduttori all'avanguardia e sostenibili dovrebbe rappresentare entro il 2030 almeno il 20 % del valore della produzione mondiale. L'industria europea sta infatti scontando la carenza di microchip e semiconduttori dovuta alla crisi finanziaria post COVID-19 e solo un incremento della produzione autoctona permetterà al nostro continente di stare al passo di <em>competitor</em> come Stati Uniti, India e Cina.</p><p lang='it'>L'ultimo aspetto da considerare è quello della digitalizzazione dei servizi pubblici, con l'obiettivo di rendere pienamente accessibili a tutti i cittadini i servizi pubblici online entro il 2030. Tutti nell'Unione europea dovremmo beneficiare di un ambiente digitale di qualità, che offra servizi e strumenti di facile uso, efficienti e personalizzati, con elevati standard in materia di sicurezza e tutela della vita privata. Solo garantendo che tutti i servizi pubblici principali saranno disponibili online per le imprese e per i cittadini, l'Europa potrà rafforzare la sua leadership digitale e affrontare le sfide che la globalizzazione le ha imposto.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="pl" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.42" speakername="Andżelika Anna Możdżanowska" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9899" time="09:38:27" url=""><p lang='pl'> – Pani Przewodnicząca! Panie Komisarzu! Czwarta rewolucja przemysłowa, sztuczna inteligencja, pandemia COVID-19 pokazały, że transformacja naszej gospodarki i społeczeństwa w kierunku bardziej cyfrowego jest naszym pilnym celem. Musimy pilnie przyspieszyć proces kształcenia i rozwoju infrastruktury cyfrowej we wszystkich krajach Unii Europejskiej. Dlatego tak ważny jest ten wspólny program „Droga ku cyfrowej dekadzie”. </p><p lang='pl'>Bardzo się cieszę, że tej ważnej debacie przysłuchuje się dzisiaj młodzież, bo to dla nich przyszłość całej Europy. Bowiem wy w tej cyfrowej gospodarce znajdujecie się najbardziej. </p><p lang='pl'>Unia Europejska musi być ambitna, nowoczesna i cyfrowa, bo zagwarantuje zysk dla Europy prawie 3 bln euro. Dla przykładu, dla mojego kraju, Polski, to blisko 500 mld złotych. Dziś niestety większość Europejczyków posiada zaledwie podstawowe kompetencje cyfrowe, a między poszczególnymi krajami utrzymują się ogromne różnice. Odsetek Europejczyków posiadających podstawowe umiejętności informatyczne waha się między 29% a 79%.</p><p lang='pl'>Dziś ten wypracowany kompromis przez nasz Parlament i Radę Europejską wymaga ambitnego podejścia i współpracy. Ustanowiliśmy konkretne cele polityki cyfrowej, umiejętności cyfrowych, infrastruktury i cyfryzacji przedsiębiorstw, a co najważniejsze przejrzyste ramy realizacji projektów wielonarodowych. Powinniśmy jednak w tym ambitnym projekcie zwrócić uwagę na kilka wrażliwych kwestii: w zakresie terminów synchronizacji publikacji krajowych cyfrowych map drogowych i osiągnięcia celów 70% dla przedsiębiorstw unijnych wykorzystujących cyfryzację w prowadzeniu działalności gospodarczej oraz 100% transformacji cyfrowej w dostępie do usług publicznych i dostępie obywateli, np. do dokumentacji medycznej. Jednak pamiętajmy, że w tym pędzie do światowej cywilizacji cyfrowej ważne, byśmy nie zapomnieli o drugim człowieku, o naszym bezpieczeństwie oraz byśmy zwrócili uwagę na zagrożenia, jakie niesie postęp technologiczny i cyfrowy świat.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.44" speakername="Andreas Schwab" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7693" time="09:40:37" url=""><p lang='de'> – Frau Präsidentin, Herr Kommissar Breton, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wir sprechen heute über den Weg zu einer digitalen Dekade, und ich möchte gerne drei Punkte herausgreifen im Anschluss an das, was Frau Kollegin Carvalho gesagt hat.</p><p lang='de'>Ich glaube zunächst einmal, dass ganz wichtig ist, dass die Europäische Union eine wertegeleitete Digitalpolitik betreibt. Und deswegen ist diese Erklärung zu den digitalen Rechten und Grundsätzen, die Sie, lieber Herr Kommissar Breton, und die Kommission vorgelegt haben, von fundamentaler Bedeutung. Die Digitalpolitik in Europa muss den gleichen Wertmaßstäben genügen wie auch die ganz klassische Wirtschafts- und Sozialpolitik, die wir betreiben. Es kann keine unterschiedliche Digitalpolitik geben.</p><p lang='de'>Deswegen glaube ich, dass wir – zum Zweiten – in den vergangenen Monaten viel erreicht haben: Das Gesetz über digitale Märkte, das Gesetz über digitale Dienste, der <em>Data Act</em> – und wir warten ja immer noch auf die Spezifikation des <em>Data Acts</em> im Hinblick auf Automobile – sind wichtige Schritte. Aber wir brauchen für all diese Schritte eine Integration in die jeweiligen Fachbereiche, und wir brauchen keine separate digitale Superrevisionsbehörde, wie das momentan im Gesetz über künstliche Intelligenz angedacht ist. Digitalpolitik muss überall dort stattfinden, wo schon heute Politik stattfindet, und es muss immer einen Ausgleich geben mit analogen Diensten und digitalen Diensten.</p><p lang='de'>Deswegen zuletzt, drittens, lieber Herr Kommissar Breton: Ich glaube, wir müssen auch über die <em>spectrum policy</em> nochmals neu nachdenken – denn wenn wir einen digitalen Binnenmarkt wirklich erreichen wollen, wenn wir wettbewerbsfähiger werden wollen in den Telekommunikationsdiensten, dann brauchen wir einen grenzüberschreitenden Markt, und dafür brauchen die Telekommunikationsanbieter mehr Möglichkeiten. Deswegen ist da auch Ihr Mut gefragt. Dazu möchte ich Sie ermutigen; das Parlament steht da an Ihrer Seite.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="pt" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.46" speakername="Carlos Zorrinho" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8067" time="09:42:35" url=""><p lang='pt'> – Senhora Presidente, Senhor Comissário, sejamos claros.</p><p lang='pt'>Num momento em que apostamos forte na Identidade Digital ao serviço de todos os cidadãos europeus, como base para termos uma televisão digital mais inclusiva e democrática, há outra identidade digital que conta: a Identidade Digital da nossa parceria, da União Europeia. Ancorada nos valores comuns, que partilhamos para a caminhada até 2030, de que são exemplo: a defesa de uma sociedade digital focada nas pessoas, inclusiva, segura e transparente, e o acesso tendencialmente universal de todos os cidadãos europeus a redes de alta qualidade, através da tecnologia, dos recursos económicos, do desenvolvimento das competências, permitindo-lhes usufruir de serviços disponíveis e, em particular, dos serviços de interesse público em formato digital. </p><p lang='pt'>É a afirmação desta identidade digital diferenciada que nos pode permitir não apenas cumprir os nossos objetivos enquanto parceria pela paz, pela liberdade e pela democracia, como também sermos relevantes e competitivos à escala global. </p><p lang='pt'>Por isso temos que combinar todas as tecnologias, incluindo as novas gerações de WI-FI, seguindo o espírito da iniciativa <em>Wifi4EU</em>, de que fui relator, e também abrir uma frente alargada de financiamento da modernização das redes, incluindo as plataformas que dela dependem. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="it" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.48" speakername="Nicola Danti" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8528" time="09:44:00" url=""><p lang='it'> – Signora Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, quella della trasformazione digitale della nostra società e della nostra economia è una delle grandi sfide dell'Unione europea.</p><p lang='it'>Bene ha fatto la Commissione a prevedere target specifici da raggiungere da qui al 2030, che ci permetteranno di giocare un ruolo a livello globale. Così come è accaduto per il Green Deal, infatti, solo se avremo obiettivi misurabili e tangibili riusciremo a monitorare i nostri progressi in questo campo.</p><p lang='it'>Mi preme sottolineare due elementi di questa strategia che considero particolarmente significativi. Il primo: la necessità di investire per garantire la diffusione massima delle competenze digitali e un numero adeguato di professionisti digitali altamente qualificati, specialmente tra i giovani, per essere competitivi anche sul mercato del lavoro. </p><p lang='it'>Il secondo elemento è la necessità di investire sulla digitalizzazione delle imprese, soprattutto delle piccole e medie imprese, per sfruttare al meglio le opportunità che la tecnologia offre loro.</p><p lang='it'>Tutto questo passerà certamente anche dalla capacità di assicurare una connettività e infrastrutture digitali sicure e resilienti che raggiungano tutti.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="hr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.50" speakername="Ladislav Ilčić" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10142" time="09:45:24" url=""><p lang='hr'> – Poštovana predsjedavajuća, dame i gospodo, jeste li se testirali? Jeste li pokušali vidjeti koliko minuta možete izdržati i slušati govornika na nekom službenom sastanku ili čak privatnom susretu bez da posegnete za svojim pametnim telefonom ne bi li vidjeli nešto jako važno što je upravo stiglo. </p><p lang='hr'>Dakle, svi mi gubimo pažnju. Svi mi tražimo atrakciju. Svi smo mi postali na neki način ovisni. I zato, kad govorimo o digitalizaciji, pogotovo o edukaciji mladih, trebamo misliti i na ljudske slabosti kako bi tehnologije zaista bile u službi čovjeka. </p><p lang='hr'>Također, trebali bismo točno znati koliko će ova digitalizacija smanjiti administraciju, koliko će naši građani i poduzetnici zaista manje plaćati administraciju i koliko će ti procesi biti jednostavniji, brži i lakši. Da se ne dogodi kao u Hrvatskoj u kojoj smo imali više digitalnih transformacija, ali za većinu javnih usluga uvijek vas traže još samo jedan papir. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.52" speakername="Deirdre Clune" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9163" time="09:46:47" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, I would say that COVID has really demonstrated the value of digitalisation and technologies, how important they are to our societies. We’ve seen the benefits of bringing people together, delivering services, allowing business to continue, and indeed delivering particularly our education services. But we can’t stop there. We need to do more. And I very much welcome the programme, the ‘Path to the Digital Decade’, and also the Digital Scoreboard, because I think it’s good to shine a light on individual countries and set targets and how we can improve our societies, our economies.</p><p lang='en'>By 2030, we want at least 80% of adults to have basic digital skills, and we must leave nobody behind. That means age, education and social background should not be a deterrent. We need to ensure that all households have gigabyte connectivity and all population areas should be covered by 5G. That’s really important. We also need to ensure that our government and our state services are delivered digitally so that we don’t leave anybody behind in this area, particularly those who are living in rural isolated areas.</p><p lang='en'>So the targets are there and it’s a challenge. But absolutely, as I started, COVID has demonstrated just how important this is for all our societies.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.54" speakername="Tsvetelina Penkova" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9918" time="09:48:11" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, dear Commissioner Breton, dear rapporteur, colleagues, strengthening the strategic digital capacity and deployment of advanced technologies will support our businesses, benefit our citizens and definitely ensure Europe’s digital autonomy. Proper implementation of Europe’s digital decade policy programme will provide citizens with better jobs, better healthcare and better public services. Digital progress is crucial if we want to achieve our climate neutral, fair and green social goals. </p><p lang='en'>However, we still have to guarantee four important things. First, better digital infrastructure and connectivity across Europe. Second, enhance partnership between Member States. Third, better digital skills. And fourth, effective public services across all the Member States. All these objectives are crucial if we want to achieve our goals for 2030 digital targets. </p><p lang='en'>Europe has the capacity to be a global digital leader where technological advancement, fair and green economic growth, social inclusion and business competitiveness are all equally respected.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="hr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.56" speakername="Valter Flego" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9728" time="09:49:32" url=""><p lang='hr'> – Poštovana predsjedavajuća, dame i gospodo, digitalna transformacija našeg društva i gospodarstva? Da. Digitalizacija? Apsolutno da. Ali ne smijemo zaboraviti utjecaj tehnologije na čovjeka. Čovjek mora uvijek biti u središtu svih programa, a stalna edukacija ljudi prioritet je u godinama ispred nas. </p><p lang='hr'>Nažalost, svjesni smo, prekomjerno korištenje digitalnih uređaja i digitalna ovisnost dio su naše svakodnevice, posebice nažalost kod mladih. Zato, poštovani povjereniče Breton, pozivam Komisiju da ojača i financijski pomogne i osnaži programe edukacije, posebice mladih ljudi, kako bi na jedan ispravan i zdrav način iskoristili mogućnosti koje su ispred nas i na tome nikada ne smije se štedjeti. </p><p lang='hr'>Digitalizacija i digitalna transformacija, naime, imat će uspjeha i smisla samo ako tu digitalizaciju, tu tehnologiju, budu koristile zdrave i sretne osobe, kako na poslu tako i kod kuće. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="pl" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.58" speakername="Elżbieta Kruk" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9841" time="09:50:45" url=""><p lang='pl'> – Pani Przewodnicząca! Trudno nie popierać celu, jakim jest postęp cyfryzacji dla zwiększenia innowacyjności, efektywności gospodarki czy usprawnienia administracji. </p><p lang='pl'>Cywilizacyjny przełom, jakiego obecnie doświadcza świat w następstwie dokonującej się czwartej rewolucji przemysłowej, niesie jednak nowe wyzwania i kontrowersje związane z wykorzystywaniem technologii cyfrowych i sztucznej inteligencji. Stwarzając ogromne szanse rozwojowe, stworzył też rozmaite zagrożenia, w tym ryzyka cyfrowych nadużyć, naruszania prywatności, inwigilacji, dehumanizacji i alienacji ludzi. Znane są liczne przypadki, w których skutkiem błędnych decyzji algorytmów komputerowych i sztucznej inteligencji jest naruszenie praw i wolności wielu obywateli. </p><p lang='pl'>Program „Droga ku cyfrowej dekadzie” nie daje dostatecznej odpowiedzi na społeczne obawy co do potencjalnych negatywnych skutków wdrażania technologii cyfrowych. Znajdujemy tu natomiast charakterystyczny dla dzisiejszych dokumentów unijnych zapis, że technologie te mają być zgodne z wartościami Unii. </p><p lang='pl'>Ale co to są te „wartości Unii”? Czy to wartości historycznie współtworzące europejskiego ducha, jak na przykład etyka chrześcijańska? Czy są raczej wyrazem lewackich dążeń ideologicznych, które zamiast dobrodziejstwa nowych technologii przyniosą nam totalitaryzm nowego wspaniałego świata?</p></speech>
        <speech lang="pl" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.60" speakername="Krzysztof Hetman" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8530" time="09:52:17" url=""><p lang='pl'> – Pani Przewodnicząca! Panie Komisarzu! Szanowni Państwo! W ostatnich latach słowa „transformacja cyfrowa” były odmieniane przez wszystkie przypadki. Pandemia COVID-19 w znacznym stopniu przyspieszyła zachodzące procesy i wymusiła na nas adaptację do nowej rzeczywistości właśnie poprzez powszechniejsze wykorzystanie technologii cyfrowych. Nie ulega jednak wątpliwości, że aby Unia Europejska mogła w naprawdę skuteczny sposób i w pełni przeprowadzić transformację cyfrową, potrzebujemy spójnej strategii. Program polityki „Droga ku cyfrowej dekadzie” do 2030 r. jest właściwym krokiem w tę stronę. </p><p lang='pl'>Program ma duży potencjał. Nakreśla ambitne cele cyfrowe dla całej Unii w zakresie priorytetowych obszarów. Będą one osiągane poprzez indywidualne ścieżki krajowe. Oczywiście w minutę nie sposób wspomnieć wszystkich założeń, ale do najważniejszych można zdecydowanie zaliczyć: umożliwienie obywatelom dostępu do usług publicznych w 100% online, znaczne zwiększenie liczby specjalistów w zakresie technologii cyfrowych, zwiększenie umiejętności cyfrowych i zwalczanie wykluczenia, a także ucyfrowienie przedsiębiorstw. Uważam, że dzięki tej strategii będziemy w stanie sprawniej osiągać wskazane cele na poziomie Unii.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="mt" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.62" speakername="Alex Agius Saliba" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9570" time="09:53:35" url=""><p lang='mt'> – President, Kummissarju, it-trasformazzjoni diġitali tal-ekonomiji u s-soċjetajiet Ewropej qiegħda timxi b'pass mgħaġġel ħafna, u dan qed iġib miegħu numru ta' opportunitajiet ġodda imma fl-istess ħin sfidi kritiċi li rridu nindirizzaw fiż-żmien ġejjieni.</p><p lang='mt'>Kriżijiet reċenti, bla dubju, jenfasizzaw ir-rwol ewlieni tat-trasformazzjoni diġitali fil-bini ta' futur sostenibbli għaċ-ċittadini Ewropej. Fl-istess ħin, dawn il-kriżijiet esponew, b'mod qawwi ħafna, il-qasma diġitali li teżisti bejn iċ-ċittadini, u l-ħtieġa li jiġu adottati soluzzjonijiet diġitali li huma aċċessibbli għal reġjuni, pajjiżi u setturi differenti. U għalhekk li neħtieġu impenji addizzjonali biex niggarantixxu tranżizzjoni ġusta, tranżizzjoni inklużiva li ma tħalli lil ħadd jaqa' lura; b'miri konkreti, investiment pubbliku u interventi f'setturi strateġiċi biex niżguraw progress ekoloġiku u diġitali għal kulħadd, inkluż l-għoti ta' protezzjonijiet u opportunitajiet anke lill-aktar komunitajiet remoti, lill-aktar komunitajiet periferali.</p><p lang='mt'>Għaldaqstant, nappoġġja l-kontribut li inizjattivi bħad-Deċennju Diġitali jista' jkollhom fil-kisba tat-trasformazzjoni diġitali koeżiva għas-soċjetà Ewropea sal-2030, b'mod partikolari li jegħleb id-distakk bejn iż-żoni rurali u urbani.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="sk" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.64" speakername="Eugen Jurzyca" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9812" time="09:55:17" url=""><p lang='sk'> – Vážená pani predsedajúca, je nepochybne dobré, že si stanovujeme ciele pre digitalizáciu. Bohužiaľ, nemáme ich celkom dobre zvolené. </p><p lang='sk'>Nemerajú výsledky pre občana. Napríklad cieľ, aby boli kľúčové verejné služby dostupné online. Nestačí predsa, že je služba dostupná online, lebo online služba môže byť urobená tak, že ňou občania stratia viac času, než keby navštívili úrad peši. Kto neverí, nech si prečíta o tom, ako fungovala online služba pre registráciu na vakcináciu proti Covidu na Slovensku, v mojom členskom štáte. </p><p lang='sk'>Namiesto toho vhodnejšie by boli ciele, ako napríklad, o koľko sa zvýšila úspora času, klesli náklady alebo o koľko sa zvýšila produktivita práce vďaka digitalizácii. Takéto ciele väčšinou v návrhu chýbajú a myslím si, že je to škoda. Som o tom presvedčený. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.66" speakername="Barbara Thaler" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10018" time="09:56:36" url=""><p lang='de'> – Frau Präsidentin, sehr geehrter Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Wir diskutieren heute unser Politikprogramm für die Digitalstrategie, um, wie man so schön sagt, fit für den Standort der Zukunft zu werden. Es geht um Infrastruktur, künstliche Intelligenz, 5G, 6G, Cloud-Computing, Blockchain und vieles mehr.</p><p lang='de'>Es geht auch um Quanten-Computing, und darauf möchte ich kurz eingehen. Der Bericht – übrigens, herzlichen Glückwunsch, Frau Berichterstatterin – streicht hervor, dass Quanten-Computing-Kapazitäten zu einer entscheidenden Voraussetzung werden. Bis 2025 wollen wir unseren ersten Quantencomputer haben, damit wir bis 2030 eine absolute Spitzenposition im Bereich Quantenkapazitäten erreichen können. Und ich finde, wir haben großes Potenzial dazu als Europäische Union, um auf diesem Gebiet wirklich weltweit Vorreiter zu werden.</p><p lang='de'>Mit ein bisschen Stolz, Herr Kommissar, darf ich sagen, dass in meiner Heimatregion – in Tirol – die weltweit erste Quantenarchitekturfirma sitzt. Für solche Firmen müssen wir die Rahmenbedingungen schaffen – so kann ein europäisches Ökosystem für Quanten-Computing die Welt verändern. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="es" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.68" speakername="Adriana Maldonado López" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9871" time="09:58:05" url=""><p lang='es'> – Señora presidenta, señor comisario, señorías, sin duda, una de las prioridades políticas de esta Comisión Europea, de este Parlamento Europeo es la Década Digital. Una Década Digital que no solamente sirve como motor de transformación, sino que este Itinerario hacia la Década Digital para 2030 pone en el horizonte problemas reales que tenemos hoy en la Unión Europea. </p><p lang='es'>Y me quiero centrar principalmente en tres de ellos, que debemos de ser capaces de abordar de una forma coordinada y, sobre todo, buscando resultados para el año 2030. Están relacionados con la reducción de la brecha digital. </p><p lang='es'>Los hombres ocupan a día de hoy ocho de cada diez puestos de trabajo en el sector de las telecomunicaciones en la Unión Europea. Por lo tanto, las mujeres siguen estando fuera de aquellos puestos de trabajo relacionados con la digitalización. </p><p lang='es'>Pero no solamente es un problema de las mujeres, también de las pymes. En la Unión Europea tenemos una baja participación de las pymes en la digitalización y debemos, como Unión Europea, apostar por ellas. </p><p lang='es'>Pero, sobre todo, también me quiero centrar en un elemento trascendental: el mundo rural. No podemos seguir creando dos Europas, a dos velocidades; la del mundo rural y la de las grandes ciudades. </p><p lang='es'>Por lo tanto, este itinerario digital tiene un objetivo claro: reducir brechas. Y nuestro cometido como Parlamento Europeo, sin duda, es hacer que sea lo más efectivo posible y, sobre todo, que sea una realidad en el año 2030. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="it" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.70" speakername="Luisa Regimenti" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9948" time="09:59:35" url=""><p lang='it'> – Signora Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, con l'incessante aumento dell'importanza e dell'utilizzo del digitale è sempre più difficile per i cittadini e le aziende rimanere al passo. </p><p lang='it'>Le nuove tecnologie contribuiscono allo sviluppo economico e sociale, ma sono accompagnate da rischi, insicurezza e disinformazione. Molte piccole e medie imprese sono state abbandonate a loro stesse durante il passaggio alla gestione informatica.</p><p lang='it'>Dedicare una maggiore percentuale del budget del dispositivo per la ripresa e la resilienza alla transizione digitale è indispensabile per dare l'opportunità a tutte le aziende di essere parte di una rete virtuale che collega e accomuna tutti i paesi membri.</p><p lang='it'>La sicurezza dei dati inoltre viene spesso sottovalutata. Informare e fornire direttive sul tema è fondamentale per la buona riuscita di questa visione. Connettere i paesi membri può e deve servire ad aumentare le opportunità finanziarie attraverso linee guida e protocolli che facilitino lo scambio dei dati. </p><p lang='it'>L'Europa dovrà dimostrarsi unita nel fissare obiettivi precisi e indicare i giusti percorsi che facilitino questo inarrestabile progresso.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="da" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.72" speakername="Christel Schaldemose" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8040" time="10:00:58" url=""><p lang='da'> – Fru formand! Hr. Kommissær! En fornøjelse! Digitaliseringen fylder stadig mere i vores samfund, i vores hverdag og i vores økonomi. Men selvom digitaliseringen allerede har ændret meget i vores liv, så skal vi turde at gå endnu længere. Digitaliseringen sikrer nemlig både arbejdspladser, vækst og velstand. Derfor er jeg glad for de ambitiøse mål, der er i programmet. Hvis EU skal i front i den digitale omstilling, og det synes jeg, at EU skal, så har vi brug for flere digitale eksperter, internet til alle, og at flere virksomheder og offentlige tjenester benytter sig af digitale løsninger. Jeg kommer selv fra et af verdens mest digitaliserede lande, og derfor kender jeg også til bagsiden af medaljen. Der er nogle, der mister deres job, når de bliver automatiseret, og der er nogle, der mangler digitale færdigheder for at kunne være med. Derfor er det også vigtigt, at vi sikrer, at der ikke er nogen, der bliver efterladt på perronen. Ingen skal efterlades i digitaliseringen, og derfor skal vi gøre en særlig indsats for at sikre det. Vi skal sørge for at efteruddanne dem, der mister deres job, og vi skal sørge for at give folk de færdigheder, der skal til, for at man kan være med i digitaliseringen. Måske endda også tilbyde, at man kan tilgå offentlige tjenester, uden at man har de her færdigheder. Vi skal altså være mere digitale, samtidig med at vi beskytter dem, der har svært ved at være med. Det forudsætningen for, at vi lykkes i EU.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.74" speakername="Romana Jerković" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10109" time="10:02:29" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, dear colleagues, Commissioner, as the energy and economic crisis continue to loom large, there is a growing risk that many European citizens and companies will fall behind and not reap the benefits of the digital transformation. To accelerate the pace of digital innovation and adoption, it is crucial that we match the 2030 target with a set of investments that will help close the digital divide and keep our ambitions high. </p><p lang='en'>First, we need to invest in people and education so that our citizens have the digital skills necessary to actively participate in the digital society. The digital decade must be inclusive and make digital technology work for people and for businesses. Second, the quality, access and transparency of public services through digitalisation should be improved and modernised across the EU. </p><p lang='en'>The point is not to win the digital race. The point is to develop and safeguard our societies. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.76" nospeaker="true" time="10:03:42" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Spontane Wortmeldungen</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="ro" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.78" speakername="Maria Grapini" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9040" time="10:03:56" url=""><p lang='ro'> – Doamnă președintă, domnule comisar, mă bucur că dezbatem acest subiect și această această problemă, digitalizarea. Sigur, știm că proverbul există în toate situațiile: „drumul spre iad e pavat cu intenții bune”.</p><p lang='ro'>Este foarte important și mă bucur că ați vorbit, domnule comisar, că nu sunt suficiente doar investițiile în tehnologie, ci avem nevoie și de creșterea competențelor, pentru că acum, când vorbim, sunt zone întregi geografice, mai ales în rural, în care nu avem nici infrastructură, nu este semnal pentru telefon despre ce digitalizare să mai vorbim? Iar competențele trebuiesc crescute concomitent cu investițiile, pentru că altfel ar fi o pierdere dacă facem investiție în digitalizare, dar nu avem competențe pentru accesare. </p><p lang='ro'>De asemenea, cred în efectele pozitive ale digitalizării, în efecte bune pentru a integra persoanele cu dizabilități, dar în aceeași măsură cred foarte mult că investițiile trebuiesc țintite spre zone geografice, spre zonele în care avem încă probleme legate de competențe și infrastructură.</p><p lang='ro'>De aceea, eu cred că digitalizarea merge mână în mână cu investițiile și merge mână în mână cu educația și creșterea competențelor digitale a tuturor cetățenilor din spațiul pieței interne.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.80" nospeaker="true" time="10:05:20" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>(Ende der spontanen Wortmeldungen)</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.82" speakername="Thierry Breton" speakerid="unknown" time="10:05:39" url=""><p lang='fr'> <em>membre de la Commission</em> <em>.</em> – Madame la Présidente, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, je vous remercie sincèrement pour le débat très enrichissant que nous avons eu aujourd’hui. Nous sommes évidemment tous conscients que nous devons agir d’urgence, avec détermination, pour construire la décennie numérique.</p><p lang='fr'>Vous nous avez déjà soutenus dans un nombre important de dossiers essentiels pour notre espace numérique, notre espace informationnel, à l’échelle de notre continent. Bien d’autres sont en cours de discussion, vous le savez. Il est donc essentiel pour nous, décideurs politiques, de tout mettre en œuvre pour que la transformation en cours réponde aux besoins et aux attentes de tous nos citoyens, je dis bien tous nos citoyens et, évidemment, de nos entreprises, qu’elles soient grandes ou petites. Il est temps de surmonter les inégalités entre ceux qui bénéficient de cette transformation et les autres, comme cela a été rappelé par nombre d’entre vous.</p><p lang='fr'>Affirmer notre identité et un modèle européen qui reflète nos valeurs dans un monde numérique devient effectivement un enjeu essentiel pour nous, mais aussi à l’échelle du continent et de la planète. C’est pour cela que le programme d’action pour la décennie numérique est si important. C’est notre feuille de route pour conduire la transition numérique auprès de nos citoyens, des gouvernements, des entreprises. C’est aussi crucial pour réduire nos dépendances technologiques et éviter d’en créer de nouvelles dans un monde qui va devenir de plus en plus complexe, on le sait.</p><p lang='fr'>La nouveauté de ce programme d’action est surtout qu’il fixe – vous l’avez rappelé à juste titre, les uns et les autres et vous-même, évidemment, Madame la rapporteure – des objectifs quantitatifs à réaliser et, ce faisant, qu’il engage les États membres dans une nouvelle gouvernance.</p><p lang='fr'>Je tiens à rappeler ici, en conclusion, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, que la Commission jouera évidemment tout son rôle pour mettre en œuvre ce programme dans les meilleurs délais. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="cs" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.84" speakername="Martina Dlabajová" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7939" time="10:08:02" url=""><p lang='cs'> <em>zpravodajka</em> <em>.</em> – Paní předsedající, pane komisaři, kolegyně, kolegové, děkuji za všechny konstruktivní připomínky, názory a vaši podporu. Cesta k digitální dekádě nebude jednoduchá. Bude se místy klikatit, často se na ní vyskytne překážka, kterou budeme muset přeskočit nebo přelézt. I přesto jsem ráda, že jsme se na ni vydali. Děkuji Evropské komisi, děkuji členským státům, že jsme našli společnou představu o tom, jak by tato cesta měla vypadat. Poděkování si zaslouží francouzské předsednictví, které položilo základy, a české předsednictví, které navázalo a jednání úspěšně zakončilo. Děkuji také všem stínovým zpravodajům a všem našim týmům. Chtěla bych, aby ještě jednou zaznělo, že jsme se dokázali společně s Komisí i s Radou dohodnout na tom, co je nutné sledovat, abychom věděli, zda se cíle digitální dekády daří plnit nebo ne. Dostatek informací a poučení se z minulých chyb jsou základním stavebním kamenem pokroku a už teď se těším na každoroční zprávu o stavu digitální dekády. </p><p lang='cs'>Digitální dekáda je politický program s konkrétními cíli a je nastavena tak, že má státy vést a ukazovat směr, jak tyto cíle úspěšně splnit. Je to společná strategie a je v zájmu všech se jí řídit. Věřím, že se mi podařilo s vaší pomocí najít ten správný mix, jak dosáhnout plné digitalizace do roku 2030. Nezapomeňme, že se celou dobu tady bavíme o 20 milionech expertů v oboru ICT, o digitálních dovednostech pro více než 360 milionů obyvatel Evropy, o zajištění milionů vysokorychlostních přípojek k internetu napříč celou EU, o vytvoření 10 000 klimaticky neutrálních, vysoce zabezpečených okrajových uzlů, o prvním počítači s kvantovým zrychlením, o užití cloudových služeb, umělé inteligence, zpracování dat velkého objemu třemi čtvrtinami podniků v EU nebo o plné digitalizaci veřejné správy a zdravotnické péče. A to vše za pouhých osm let.</p><p lang='cs'>Možná vám to připadá stále jako science-fiction nebo pohádka, ale já věřím, že se v roce 2030 ukáže, že jsme udělali všechno správně. Nyní je to na vás a na vašem hlasování. Děkuji za pozornost a těším se, jak dnešní hlasování dopadne.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.86" speakername="Evelyn Regner" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9145" time="10:10:29" url=""><p lang='de'>Die Aussprache ist geschlossen.</p><p lang='de'>Die Abstimmung findet heute, Donnerstag, 24. November 2022, statt.</p><p lang='de'> <em> <em>Schriftliche Erklärungen (Artikel 171)</em> </em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="pl" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.88" speakername="Karol Karski" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9100" time="10:10:29" url=""><p lang='pl'> <em>na piśmie</em> <em>.</em> – Program „Droga ku cyfrowej dekadzie” przy udanej realizacji jego założeń może, według istniejących obliczeń, przyczynić się do uzyskania dodatkowych 2,8 bln euro w całej Unii. W przypadku przyspieszenia wdrażania technologii cyfrowych w Polsce i zrealizowaniu założeń unijnego planu, możliwe jest uzyskanie w PKB dodatkowych 491 mld złotych do 2030 roku. Choć większość Europejczyków posiada podstawowe kompetencje cyfrowe, to między poszczególnymi krajami utrzymują się znaczne różnice – odsetek ludności posiadającej przynajmniej podstawowe umiejętności informatyczne waha się od 29% do 79%. Aby osiągnąć zakładany w programie cel, zgodnie z którym do 2030 roku 80% populacji powinno dysponować podstawowymi umiejętnościami cyfrowymi, konieczne jest przyspieszenie procesu kształcenia i rozwoju infrastruktury cyfrowej. Jeżeli w ciągu ostatnich pięciu lat ogólny wskaźnik rozpowszechnienia podstawowych umiejętności cyfrowych wzrósł jedynie o 4-5% - stawia to pod znak zapytania takie cele jak wzrost liczby przedsiębiorstw intensywnie wykorzystujących technologie chmury cyfrowej czy cyfryzacja usług publicznych. Jestem zadowolony z kompromisu wypracowanego przez PE i Radę UE. Zwłaszcza należy podkreślić znaczenie mechanizmu zarządzania ich realizacją i monitorowania wyników, który został zaplanowany tak by nie generować obciążeń dla administracji publicznych p.cz. Pewne niedociągnięcia widzę w niedostatecznie zsynchronizowanych terminach publikacji krajowych cyfrowych map drogowych oraz w zbyt małym czasie na opracowanie krajowych cyfrowych map drogowych.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.89" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="10:10:29" url="">The European Year of Youth 2022 Legacy (debate)</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.91" speakername="Evelyn Regner" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9145" time="10:10:46" url=""><p lang='de'>Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über die Erklärung der Kommission zum Europäischen Jahr der Jugend 2022 – Vermächtnis (<a href="#reds:DirContProc/RSP-2022-2953" data-rel="reds" redmap-uri="/reds:DirContProc/RSP-2022-2953">2022/2953(RSP)</a>). </p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.93" speakername="Thierry Breton" speakerid="unknown" time="10:11:13" url=""><p lang='fr'> <em>membre de la Commission</em> <em>.</em> – Madame la Présidente, Mesdames et Messieurs les députés, tout d’abord, au nom de ma collègue Mariya Gabriel, je souhaiterais ici vous faire part des dernières observations préliminaires de la Commission concernant le bilan que nous tirons de l’Année de la jeunesse 2022.</p><p lang='fr'>Cette Année européenne de la jeunesse avait un objectif clair: placer les jeunes au centre, écouter ce qu’ils ont à nous dire et agir en conséquence, en renforçant leurs compétences pour qu’ils puissent développer leurs idées et surtout en les préparant à participer aux débats politiques. Cela a permis à davantage de jeunes de se mobiliser, de s’impliquer aussi au niveau politique, de s’engager et de sensibiliser leurs pairs aux opportunités qu’offre l’Union européenne. Selon les organisateurs des différentes activités, ce sont plus de 150 millions de citoyens européens qui ont été sensibilisés. Ces opportunités ont ouvert de nouveaux canaux permettant aux jeunes de faire entendre leur point de vue, de s’engager dans l’élaboration de politiques à différents niveaux et donc d’influencer leur contenu.</p><p lang='fr'>Mais au delà de cet aspect, il est maintenant temps d’échanger et de réfléchir sur ce qui a bien fonctionné et sur ce qui peut être davantage développé. La Commission a ainsi entamé un processus de bilan des résultats obtenus et notre débat aujourd’hui contribue à ce processus. Les retours seront accueillis auprès des coordinateurs nationaux de l’Année européenne de la jeunesse, des acteurs de la jeunesse eux-mêmes et des jeunes, et ils feront partie du rapport de la mise en œuvre de l’Année qui sera ensuite communiqué aux colégislateurs avant la fin de l’année 2023. L’ensemble de ces réflexions nourriront aussi l’évaluation de mi-parcours d’ici fin 2023 de la stratégie de l’Union en faveur de la jeunesse pour la période 2019-2027, notre plan commun à long terme visant, je le rappelle, à mobiliser les jeunes et à les connecter en leur donnant les moyens d’agir.</p><p lang='fr'>Sans attendre, nous avons déjà pu constater que l’Année européenne de la jeunesse a permis un certain nombre de réalisations majeures. Tout d’abord, les 28 et 29 octobre, les couloirs du Parlement européen à Bruxelles résonnaient des voix de plus de 1 300 jeunes militants qui ont participé à la conférence «LevelUp! Youth Boot Camp». Ces jeunes ont développé leurs compétences dans le cadre d’ateliers et d’événements de mise en réseau. L’événement a lui-même résonné, si je puis dire, sur les réseaux sociaux, avec près de 40 000 jeunes des quatre coins d’Europe qui se sont manifestés et qui ont communiqué ensemble. C’est l’effet d’entraînement que nous souhaitions créer.</p><p lang='fr'>Par ailleurs, plus de 8 000 autres activités sont à répertorier sur le portail européen de la jeunesse. Si la majorité de ces activités se sont déroulées en présentiel ou en format hybride, la mobilisation des réseaux sociaux et des campagnes en ligne ont permis de toucher des millions de jeunes partout dans l’Union.</p><p lang='fr'>L’année a donné lieu à de nouveaux partenariats et à de nouvelles connexions, y compris au sein de la Commission. Citons par exemple la nouvelle initiative d’automatisation sociale, dite ALMA – orientation, apprentissage, maîtrise, réussite –, dans le cadre du Fonds social européen plus. Elle vise à aider les jeunes défavorisés à s’intégrer sur le marché du travail et au sein de la société de leur pays d’origine, à la suite, par exemple, d’une expérience professionnelle ou autre dans un autre État membre.</p><p lang='fr'>Nous avons aussi continué à renforcer les initiatives existantes auprès de la très populaire Semaine européenne du codage afin d’assurer l’égalité d’accès aux compétences numériques à tous les enfants, indépendamment de leur milieu économique ou de l’argent.</p><p lang='fr'>Deux initiatives importantes dans le domaine de la recherche et de l’innovation méritent aussi d’être mises en avant. Dans le cadre du programme des villes européennes de la science, Leiden a accueilli la 33ᵉ édition du concours européen des jeunes scientifiques, rassemblant 132 jeunes, très brillants esprits, sélectionnés parmi plus de 65 000 participants du monde entier. Nous avons également lancé une nouvelle infrastructure européenne de recherche intitulée «Growing Up in Digital Europe – EuroCohort», qui constituera une source unique de données statistiques de haute qualité et fiables pour soutenir le développement de politiques sociales et améliorer le bien-être des enfants, des jeunes et de leurs familles dans toute l’Europe.</p><p lang='fr'>La Commission a également lancé de nouvelles initiatives qui donnent aux jeunes des opportunités et des espaces pour s’exprimer, pour faire entendre leurs visions et leurs idées, pour influencer et inspirer leurs pairs et la société au sens large. Il s’agit entre autres de la plateforme Youth Voices, du vivier de jeunes journalistes européens, des dialogues politiques avec les commissaires et les différents réseaux d’ambassadeurs de la jeunesse.</p><p lang='fr'>Enfin, de nouveaux partenariats et de nouveaux liens ont été établis entre les institutions de l’Union européenne, les États membres et les organisations de jeunesse. Au sein de la Commission européenne, nous réfléchissons actuellement à la manière de poursuivre la coopération avec le groupe de coordinateurs nationaux de l’Année européenne de la jeunesse ainsi qu’avec les points de contact nationaux et les parties prenantes. Outre les représentants nommés par les États membres, plus de 120 acteurs de la jeunesse faisaient partie de ce groupe. Des représentants du Parlement européen, du Comité des régions, du Comité économique et social européen faisaient également partie de ce réseau. Et je tiens à vous préciser ici que cette collaboration a été extrêmement précieuse.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.95" speakername="Sabine Verheyen" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7407" time="10:17:03" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>im Namen der PPE-Fraktion</em> <em>.</em> – Frau Präsidentin, sehr geehrter Herr Kommissar! Das Europäische Jahr der Jugend war die richtige Initiative zur richtigen Zeit, denn in der Corona-Pandemie waren die jungen Menschen besonders solidarisch. Es war deswegen nur angemessen, dass wir sie 2022 zu unserer Priorität gemacht haben.</p><p lang='de'>Ich glaube aber, wir hätten es noch besser machen können, indem wir stärker in die Basis hinein, nach unten hin kommuniziert hätten. Viele junge Menschen wussten überhaupt nicht, dass wir ein Europäisches Jahr der Jugend hatten. Das ist dringend verbesserungsbedürftig. Wir hätten sie von Anfang an noch stärker mit einbinden müssen, und zwar auch an der Basis und nicht nur in der <em>Brussels bubble</em>. </p><p lang='de'>Wir haben in den Austauschen mit den jungen Menschen viel gelernt in diesem Jahr: was sie bewegt, was ihre Wünsche an die Politik sind. Jetzt kommt es aber vor allem darauf an, was wir daraus machen. Das Jahr darf kein Strohfeuer sein, das am 31. Dezember verlischt. Es muss ein langfristiges Vermächtnis haben, denn wir brauchen echte politische Beteiligung junger Menschen, und wir sind ihnen auch greifbare Outputs schuldig.</p><p lang='de'>Wir haben uns letztes Jahr hier versprochen, dass das Europäische Jahr der Jugend nicht nur ein <em>nice to have</em> sein soll, und jetzt ist unsere Chance zu beweisen, dass wir es ernst meinen. Lassen Sie uns den Input der jungen Menschen aufnehmen und Strukturen für eine bessere Beteiligung schaffen!</p><p lang='de'>Themen wie Partizipation junger Menschen und bessere Teilhabe – zum Beispiel ein <em>Youth Test, </em>ein struktureller Dialog mit jungen Menschen –, Themen wie nachhaltige Klima- und Umweltpolitik, das Thema mentale Gesundheit, das Thema Jobs und Skills – und da ein Dankeschön an die Kommission, dass das nächste Jahr das Europäische Jahr der Skills wird; auch das greift schon einen Aspekt, den die jungen Menschen nach vorne gebracht haben, auf – und das Thema Digitalisierung: Das waren die <em>Big Five</em>, die wir auch in Zukunft verfolgen müssen; das waren die Themen, die sowohl beim EYE-Event, aber auch bei vielen, vielen anderen Jugendveranstaltungen hier immer wieder in den Fokus gerückt wurden.</p><p lang='de'>Lassen Sie uns auch in den nächsten Jahren gemeinsam mit der jungen Generation daran arbeiten und nicht über die Köpfe der jungen Menschen hinweg – das wäre in meinen Augen der wichtigste Output aus diesem Jahr, dass wir mit den jungen Menschen gemeinsam agieren.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="sv" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.97" speakername="Heléne Fritzon" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9736" time="10:19:23" url=""><p lang='sv'> <em>för S&amp;D-gruppen</em> <em>.</em> – Fru talman! Kommissionär! Vi har krig i Europa, vi har en klimatkris och vi har fortfarande följder av pandemin som plågar oss. Allt detta upplever ungdomar runtom i Europa och känner stor oro för. I mitt land, Sverige, svarar den unga generationen att hoppfullheten minskar. Färre än hälften ser i dag ljust på sin framtid. Därför är det så viktigt att vi tar barns och ungas oro på allvar, och därför var det välkommet med ett europeiskt ungdomsår.</p><p lang='sv'>EU har så mycket att erbjuda unga: högklassiga studentutbyten inom Erasmus, möjlighet att tågluffa och upptäcka Europa, ett första jobb eller en praktikplats i ett annat EU-land, kanske här i parlamentet. Vi kan dock göra ännu mer. Vi behöver fler studentutbyten, smidigare tågsträckor och anständiga löner och villkor. </p><p lang='sv'>Europaåret för ungdomar måste bli mer än enskilda event och seminarier. Det måste bli en kickstart för en politik för unga som visar fortsatt solidaritet med Ukraina, som är jämställd och inkluderande och som på riktigt tar klimatkrisen på allvar. Det är nämligen mycket som står på spel i vårt EU. Låt Europaåret för ungdomar bli en hoppets vändpunkt för alla unga i EU, för framtiden för vår union.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.99" speakername="Laurence Farreng" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9723" time="10:21:03" url=""><p lang='fr'> <em>au nom du groupe Renew</em> <em>.</em> – Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, oui, c’était une bonne idée de faire de 2022 l’Année européenne de la jeunesse. J’ai défendu cette idée quand elle a été présentée par la présidente von der Leyen. Nous étions en pleine COVID. Les jeunes avaient souffert lourdement du confinement dans leur vie quotidienne. Cela a bouleversé leur quotidien. Oui, c’était une bonne idée, mais on ne peut pas s’arrêter là. </p><p lang='fr'>Alors oui, il y a eu des progrès. L’implication des jeunes a progressé, mais nous n’avons abouti à rien de concret. Et ça, c’est le pire en politique: les promesses non tenues, de celles qui font les abstentionnistes, qui font que les citoyens se détournent de nous. Nous avons demandé par exemple de respecter les engagements sur la conférence sur l’avenir de l’Europe en consultant les jeunes sur les grandes politiques qui les concernent et qui les touchent. Nous attendions cette annonce lors du discours sur l’état de l’Union d’Ursula von der Leyen, mais elle n’est pas venue. </p><p lang='fr'>Nous avons demandé d’engager un cadre européen pour des stages de qualité et justement rémunérés. Nous avons aussi demandé un cadre pour la santé mentale des jeunes. Rien de concret n’a été annoncé. </p><p lang='fr'>Alors, je suis particulièrement fière, avec mon groupe Renew, mes collègues, Dragoş Pîslaru, d’avoir mis en place un groupe de travail qui met les jeunes au cœur de la consultation politique et de nos réflexions. Nous avançons ensemble. </p><p lang='fr'>Mais, au plan de l’Union européenne, le travail reste à aboutir. C’est pour cela que l’Année européenne de la jeunesse doit se poursuivre encore six mois et c’est ce que nous demandons dans cette résolution.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="es" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.101" speakername="Diana Riba i Giner" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9954" time="10:22:43" url=""><p lang='es'> <em>en nombre del Grupo Verts/ALE</em> <em>.</em> – Señora presidenta, comisario, este Año Europeo de la Juventud ha puesto a nuestras instituciones ante el espejo y, desafortunadamente, no todo lo que el reflejo nos devuelve nos gusta.</p><p lang='es'>Los jóvenes siguen enfrentándose a la precariedad y a una transición, casi siempre difícil, a la vida laboral.</p><p lang='es'>Los impactos de la pandemia, la reciente guerra en Ucrania, el aumento del coste de la vida, la pobreza energética y una emergencia climática que hace difícil imaginar un futuro, solo han contribuido a empeorar la ya crítica situación de la salud mental de nuestras niñas y adolescentes.</p><p lang='es'>Ser mujer joven, ser un joven de la comunidad LGTBIQ+, ser joven migrante, joven, refugiado, joven con discapacidad o varias de estas cosas a la vez, supone grandes desafíos como es el hecho de disponer de menos oportunidades.</p><p lang='es'>Pero, como resumen, les diría que este año nos deja una buena noticia, una lección y varios retos. La buena noticia es, por ejemplo, este debate, que nos permite nombrar problemas que muchas veces se han relegado a los márgenes y poner a los jóvenes en el centro de la agenda. </p><p lang='es'>La lección: un año europeo que no se prepara con anticipación difícilmente puede fijar objetivos sólidos y alcanzar metas ambiciosas.</p><p lang='es'>Y los retos: tenemos que materializar lo que desde este Parlamento hemos pedido decididamente, esto es, un marco común para garantizar una remuneración justa de los períodos de prácticas, la accesibilidad a una atención de salud mental libre de estigmas y, en última instancia, pero quizás el reto más importante, involucrar y escuchar a los jóvenes en la preparación de todas las políticas europeas y también en la evaluación de su impacto.</p><p lang='es'>En definitiva, tenemos que impulsar cambios estructurales para construir un sistema político europeo más inclusivo con los jóvenes desde el antirracismo, libre de discriminación y de violencia de género. Necesitamos mecanismos y políticas que reflejen positivamente la posición y el papel que juegan los jóvenes como miembros activos de la sociedad.</p><p lang='es'>Durante el Año Europeo de la Juventud hemos reivindicado que se pongan las voces de los jóvenes en el centro y ahora reivindicamos que estas voces permanezcan.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.103" speakername="Aurélia Beigneux" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9606" time="10:25:38" url=""><p lang='fr'> <em>au nom du groupe ID</em> <em>.</em> – Madame le Président, Monsieur le Commissaire, la conception que vous avez de la jeunesse de nos différentes nations est complètement dévoyée. Cette proposition de résolution sur l’Année européenne de la jeunesse est donc l’occasion de rappeler quelques points. </p><p lang='fr'>Vous ne parlez qu’à la jeunesse des métropoles, celle que vous représentez, portant le voile, pendant que la jeunesse iranienne cherche désespérément à s’en débarrasser. Celle que vous représentez adhère aux idées woke, LGBT et progressistes, alors que leur priorité réelle et immédiate est celle des fins de mois et d’un marché du travail saturé. </p><p lang='fr'>Pour le reste de la jeunesse, le constat est simple: vous ne l’écoutez pas et elle ne vous écoute pas. La preuve la plus flagrante de cette manipulation idéologique, ce sont les journées EYE au Parlement européen, théâtre de l’extrême gauche militante, qui fait coexister les ateliers féministes, islamistes FEMYSO, les espaces de discussion sur le racisme et les lieux de débat sur l’identité transgenre – la vérité fait mal à entendre, je le sais. </p><p lang='fr'>La jeunesse européenne doit savoir que c’est ainsi que vous représentez ses préoccupations du quotidien. Pour vous, la jeunesse n’est qu’une métaphore de la gauche. Vous réunissez systématiquement dans cet hémicycle les jeunes des grandes écoles, des ONG et des associations fédéralistes en faisant croire que ces personnes représentent la jeunesse européenne. La pluralité d’opinions est inexistante à chaque fois que vous leur donnez la parole. En témoigne notamment votre enquête en ligne sur les valeurs européennes. Véritable flop d’ailleurs, qui n’aura reçu que 5 000 réponses sur les 88 millions de jeunes que compte notre continent. </p><p lang='fr'>La jeunesse, c’est l’argument facile pour justifier votre campagne fédéraliste, gauchiste et antinationale. C’est faire croire aux peuples européens que les nouvelles générations sont prêtes à ratifier le projet d’États-Unis d’Europe préparé par de vieux fédéralistes déçus par les résultats électoraux.</p><p lang='fr'>Mais s’il y a bien une constante depuis que la société moderne existe, c’est que la jeunesse a toujours refusé que l’on pense à sa place. Ne mettons pas dans le même panier idéologique des jeunes de nos 27 nations si différentes. La jeunesse est en première ligne face à la crise, face à la difficulté d’entreprendre et face à la concurrence internationale. La vérité, c’est que nos jeunes combattent tous les jours les mêmes difficultés que le reste des Européens. Alors, pour la prochaine Année européenne de la jeunesse, sortez de votre délire progressiste, allez à leur rencontre dans les différents pays, plutôt que de faire venir les fils de la bourgeoisie des riches métropoles de notre continent.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="pl" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.105" speakername="Elżbieta Kruk" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9841" time="10:28:24" url=""><p lang='pl'> <em>w imieniu grupy ECR</em> <em>.</em> – Pani Przewodnicząca! W październiku 2021 r. Komisja Europejska przedstawiła formalny wniosek w sprawie ogłoszenia roku 2022 Europejskim Rokiem Młodzieży.</p><p lang='pl'>Krytykowaliśmy wówczas późne przyjęcie tej inicjatywy. Było bowiem oczywiste, że taki pośpiech spowoduje, że osiągnięcie wyznaczonych celów będzie zbyt dużym wyzwaniem. Teraz się to potwierdza. Trzeba było słuchać racjonalnych argumentów i przewidzieć wystarczający czas, aby przygotować realne działania w tak trudnych dla młodzieży czasach.</p><p lang='pl'>To w szczególności młodych ludzi dotknęły wszak gospodarcze, psychologiczne i społeczne konsekwencje bezprecedensowych środków, wprowadzonych pod pozorem walki z COVID-19, takich jak lockdowny czy segregacja ludzi zamiast podnoszonej tu równości. Zamykanie szkół spowodowało szkody dla edukacji. Młodzi ludzie stracili też możliwość szkolenia, wolontariatu czy pracy. A i dziś nie ułatwiają im życia napięcia gospodarcze i polityczne spowodowane między innymi agresją Rosji na Ukrainę.</p><p lang='pl'>Nie zmieni tego rezolucja, która ma na celu ustanowienie dziedzictwa Europejskiego Roku Młodzieży. Roku, w którym paradoksalnie średnio blisko 14 % młodych ludzi poniżej 25 roku życia w Unii Europejskiej było bez pracy.</p><p lang='pl'>Znajdują się też w rezolucji zapisy, których motywem jest ideologia, a nie rzeczywista troska o dobro młodzieży, oraz apele o podjęcie działań niezgodnych z zasadą pomocniczości. Do nich należy wezwanie państw członkowskich do włączenia edukacji obywatelskiej – i to w formie obywatelstwa globalnego i unijnego – do krajowych programów nauczania, choć obszar edukacji należy do wyłącznej kompetencji państw.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.107" speakername="Niyazi Kizilyürek" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9823" time="10:30:16" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>on behalf of The Left Group</em> <em>.</em> – Madam President, the EU today is admittedly in a very difficult position. In just a decade it has experienced a worldwide economic crisis, a pandemic of a deadly virus and the consequences of an aggression, of a war. At the same time, the effects of the climate crisis are intensifying. The youth has fewer employment opportunities. </p><p lang='en'>For the first time since the Second World War, the youth is experiencing a lower standard of living compared to their parents. It was in this context that we have decided to dedicate the year 2022 to youth and have set four main objectives: to renew the positive perspectives for young people and help them overcome the effects of pandemic on their lives; to support and empower young people to become active and engaged citizens; to better inform young generations about opportunities available to them from public policies at EU, national, regional and local levels; and to mainstream youth policy across all relevant Union policy fields. </p><p lang='en'>However, in order to meet the EU’s expectations, it takes much more than designating a European Year. We have to increase public spending on education so that every child can have a high quality education, provide employment opportunities for everyone, increase wages and ban unpaid traineeships. Racism and other forms of discrimination are diseases that cut through our society to undermine our values. We should treat this immediately. </p><p lang='en'>We have to focus on combating discrimination, address the challenges faced by young people who are discriminated. The creation of a fully-fledged EU youth test that will not merely become a bureaucratic checklist, but rather tackle these issues in a holistic way, can help achieve our aims. </p><p lang='en'>Finally, we have to extend the year until 9 May and, more importantly, to defend and promote the legacy of the European Year of Youth. As the lyrics of a Greek song tells: ‘defend the child, because if a child is saved, there is hope’. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="it" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.109" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:16" url=""><p lang='it'> <em>PRESIDENZA DELL'ON. PINA PICIERNO </em> <br /> <em>Vicepresidente</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="it" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.111" speakername="Chiara Gemma" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9749" time="10:32:38" url=""><p lang='it'> – Signora Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, qualche rapida considerazione a conclusione di questo Anno europeo dei giovani. </p><p lang='it'>Ho girato tante scuole, ho aperto le officine europee, luoghi di incontro e confronto dove costruire una partecipazione attiva e responsabile, ho ascoltato tanti giovani e ho avvertito in loro il bisogno sempre più forte di conoscenza del proprio sé emozionale.</p><p lang='it'>Se la politica vuole davvero incidere sulla crescita dei nostri giovani, occorre promuovere una scuola che sappia adottare una valutazione formativa attenta ai volti e alle emozioni più che ai prodotti e ai processi cognitivi.</p><p lang='it'>Occorre ristabilire un dialogo autentico con i giovani e per farlo bisogna sedersi in mezzo a loro, perché sono stanchi di sentirsi dire "devi essere più competente, devi essere responsabile, devi essere capace di progettarti, devi essere resiliente". Io ho provato a sedermi in mezzo a loro e a confrontarmi con loro, ho compreso tante cose, ma una fra tutte: sono giovani a cui piacerebbe una scuola basata su emozioni profonde e relazioni autentiche e non solo sulla mera conoscenza o su sterili voti, che poco hanno a che fare con il proprio sé emozionale. </p><p lang='it'>Ho promesso loro che questa scuola è possibile, con pazienza e con coraggio continueremo a costruirla insieme.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="pl" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.113" speakername="Tomasz Frankowski" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9733" time="10:34:12" url=""><p lang='pl'> – Pani Przewodnicząca! Panie Komisarzu! Europejski Rok Młodzieży 2022 jest dowodem zaangażowania Unii Europejskiej w sprawy młodych i przyszłych pokoleń. Jednak nasze działania na rzecz młodych ludzi nie mogą się skończyć z dniem 31 grudnia. Musimy wykorzystać długoterminowe dziedzictwo tego roku, ponieważ potrzebujemy prawdziwego uczestnictwa młodych ludzi w polityce. Jesteśmy im winni konkretne wyniki. </p><p lang='pl'>Ubolewam nad sytuacją, w jakiej rozpoczął się rok, a zwłaszcza nad pospiesznym tempem przyjęcia rozporządzenia, co później opóźniło realizację i finansowanie wielu projektów. Mam nadzieję, że w przyszłości Komisja dopilnuje, by europejskie lata mogły zostać przygotowane w odpowiednim czasie dla wszystkich zainteresowanych stron. </p><p lang='pl'>W trakcie tego roku, podczas spotkań z młodymi ludźmi wiele się od nich nauczyliśmy. Wiemy, co jest dla nich ważne, jakie są ich życzenia dotyczące polityki. Zobowiązujemy się do słuchania głosów młodych ludzi, gdyż chcemy wspólnie pracować nad kształtowaniem przyszłości Unii Europejskiej, uwzględniając ich aspiracje. </p><p lang='pl'>Ten kończący się Europejski Rok Młodzieży powinien doprowadzić do zmiany sposobu, w jaki włączamy młodych ludzi w proces kształtowania polityki i podejmowania decyzji. Czy to w kwestiach klimatu, spraw społecznych czy rozwoju cyfrowego, młodzi ludzie są w centrum naszej polityki i priorytetów politycznych. Są przede wszystkim przyszłością naszej wspólnej Europy.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.115" speakername="Petra Kammerevert" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7195" time="10:36:03" url=""><p lang='de'> – Frau Präsidentin, Herr Kommissar, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Eine am Montag veröffentlichte Studie zeigt: Mehr als zwei Drittel der Jugendlichen sorgen sich um die Zukunft und bewerten die allgemeine Situation schlechter als jemals zuvor. Krieg in Europa, Inflation, Klimawandel, die Wirtschafts- und Energiekrise schaffen ein massives Gefühl von Unsicherheit; daran konnte auch das Europäische Jahr der Jugend nichts ändern.</p><p lang='de'>Und wie vor einem Jahr stehe ich hier und erhebe dieselben Forderungen: Schaffen Sie endlich unbezahlte Praktika ab! Eine angemessene Vergütung für geleistete Arbeit ist eine Frage des Respekts und der Chancengerechtigkeit für junge Menschen. Ich will nicht, dass nur Jugendliche aus reichen Elternhäusern sich ein Praktikum leisten können. Und lassen Sie uns gemeinsam an Strukturen arbeiten, die dauerhaft eine spürbare Beteiligung junger Menschen sicherstellen!</p><p lang='de'>Statt zu handeln, hat die Kommission es jedoch vorgezogen, mit einem Veranstaltungsmapping unter Beweis zu stellen, dass sie auch kartographisch tätig sein kann. Über 8 000 Aktivitäten wurden kartographiert – viele davon hätten sowieso stattgefunden. So diente diese Fleißarbeit eher der Selbstbestätigung. Das Jahr ging an den Jugendlichen weitgehend unbemerkt vorbei, ohne dass auch nur irgendwas für sie dabei herausgekommen wäre.</p><p lang='de'>Deshalb fordern wir, das Jahr bis zum 8. Mai 2023 zu verlängern, um in der zusätzlichen Zeit endlich etwas zu liefern, das dem Jahr doch noch zum Erfolg verhelfen könnte. Legen Sie endlich einen Vorschlag zum Verbot unbezahlter Praktika vor und schlagen Sie wenigstens Ratsschlussfolgerungen zur Einbindung von Kindern und Jugendlichen in politische Entscheidungen auf allen Ebenen vor! Ein halbgarer Jugendtest, der eher einem betreuten Gesprächskreis ähnelt, als dass er wirkliche Mitbestimmung darstellt, interessiert niemand.</p><p lang='de'>Lassen Sie uns gemeinsam an entsprechenden Maßnahmen bis zum 9. Mai arbeiten und diese auf den Weg bringen – ansonsten bleibt das Europäische Jahr der Jugend eine Farce.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.117" speakername="Dragoş Pîslaru" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9934" time="10:38:13" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, dear Commissioner, indeed the European Year of Youth 2022 was a good decision. And this was a good decision because it allowed us to listen better to our young generation. In my political group, in Renew, we had the Renew Europe Task Force set to have meetings and several interactions with the young people. Our youth political organisations have been involved in, and we’ve exchanged about, the youth’s needs: about the need for paid internships, about the need for learning opportunities, about the need for digitalisation, a more inclusive society, about the mental health challenges, about the feeling of belonging, about the need for their access to decision-making process.</p><p lang='en'>And I’m really glad that we have young people that are present with us today and will hear us. The fact that we are not going to take all these things easily; we will try to put together the implementation for that.</p><p lang='en'>One important part is related to the investment in the young generation, the next generation. We have the Child Guarantee, we have the Youth Guarantee, and we need to push that further. But then if we care about the youth, we should have them on board today, not in a distant future. We should allow them to be part in designing their future today. If we want better policies for youth, we need to have you, the young people, involved in decisions, and having this youth impact test mainstream today. To say that we care about young people, it means that we need to get them on board with us for their good.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.119" speakername="Malte Gallée" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10146" time="10:40:01" url=""><p lang='de'> – Frau Präsidentin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen, Herr Kommissar! Man sagt ja immer: Jedem Anfang wohnt ein Zauber inne. Und ich glaube, das ist mit dem Leben tatsächlich genauso. Ich würde nämlich sagen – wenn ich so selber zurückschaue –, die ersten zehn Jahre, die haben sich so viel länger angefühlt als die letzten zehn Jahre, die ich jetzt auf dem Planeten bin. Deswegen finde ich den Fokus auf die Jugend extrem wichtig – das heißt, dass es das Europäische Jahr der Jugend gab, das war eine supergute Idee, auch wenn keiner etwas davon mitbekommen hat, es kein Geld dafür gab und keine Gesetze für die Jugend auf den Weg gekommen sind.</p><p lang='de'>Das Europäische Jahr der Jugend droht quasi einfach nur so zu verpuffen wie der Vogel des Jahres – das ist der Wiedehopf. Und genau das müssen wir verhindern. Das Europäische Jahr der Jugend, das muss jetzt einfach nur der Startschuss sein für einen ganz klaren Fokus auf die Jugend, und ich glaube, die Kommission ist da schon auf einem einigermaßen guten Weg und hat wirklich auch verstanden, dass es, um glückliche Menschen auf diesem Kontinent zu schaffen, natürlich wichtig ist, dass man das Glück der Jugend schafft.</p><p lang='de'>Aber dafür, wie gesagt, muss noch einiges auf den Weg kommen. Wir brauchen ein Verbot von unbezahlten Praktika – das wurde schon so oft angesprochen. Wir müssen endlich etwas für die mentale Gesundheit unserer jungen Menschen tun, weil das ein Riesenproblem ist auf dem gesamten Kontinent. Wir müssen das Europäische Jahr der Jugend natürlich verlängern, damit die Leute auf diesem Kontinent noch wirklich etwas davon mitbekommen. Und ich möchte Sie auch darum bitten, digitale Beteiligungsformate für die Jugend an unseren demokratischen Prozessen zu schaffen, damit die Hürden gesenkt werden.</p><p lang='de'> <em>(Der Redner ist damit einverstanden, eine Wortmeldung nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“ zu beantworten.)</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.121" speakername="Niklas Nienaß" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9903" time="10:42:15" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Wortmeldung nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“</em> <em>.</em> – Sehr geehrter Herr Gallée! Gegenüber dem Wiedehopf gibt es schon einen Unterschied: Der Wiedehopf wird nämlich geschützt im besonderen Jahr.</p><p lang='de'>Deswegen würde mich interessieren: Wir haben aktuell die Situation, dass sehr viele junge Menschen mentale Probleme haben, dass gerade sehr viele junge Menschen mit Zukunftsängsten zu kämpfen haben – Klimawandel, ein Krieg. Welche Maßnahmen der Kommission würden Sie als wichtig sehen, um da wirklich Menschen zu unterstützen?</p><p lang='de'>Was kann die Europäische Kommission wirklich tun, um die mentale Gesundheit von jungen Menschen zu unterstützen und dafür zu sorgen, dass in Europa niemand mehr über Gewalt gegen sich selbst nachdenkt, über Selbstmord nachdenkt, und wir wirklich dazu kommen, dass wieder eine Zukunftspositivität entsteht?</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.123" speakername="Malte Gallée" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10146" time="10:43:12" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Antwort auf eine Wortmeldung nach dem Verfahren der „blauen Karte“</em> <em>.</em> – Was natürlich in allererster Linie das Allerwichtigste ist, ist, dass überhaupt die Lebensgrundlage für junge Menschen, auf diesem Planeten weiter zu existieren, geschaffen wird, das heißt, die Eindämmung der Klimakrise muss natürlich die absolute, höchste Priorität haben, weil das natürlich auch für die jungen Menschen die größte Bedrohung ist. Wenn wir darüber nachdenken, dass wir mit unserem CO2-Ausstoß so weitermachen wie bisher, dann ist in 100 Jahren dieser Planet nicht mehr wahnsinnig bewohnbar. So, das steht natürlich erst mal über allem.</p><p lang='de'>Dann gibt es viele weitere Projekte, die jungen Menschen wirklich Perspektiven schaffen und die Perspektiven eröffnen. Das sind Angebote zum Reisen, das sind Angebote, den Kontinent kennenzulernen. Das sind natürlich, genau wie es auch schon angesprochen wurde, ein Verbot von unbezahlten Praktika, dass wir den jungen Menschen, die eben nicht die finanziellen Ressourcen haben, wirklich auch die gleichen Chancen bieten, damit diese nicht in diese gleichen Muster verfallen und aufgefressen werden von einem System, das sie letztendlich eigentlich nur als billige Arbeitskräfte missbraucht.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.125" speakername="Gunnar Beck" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9604" time="10:44:34" url=""><p lang='de'> – Frau Präsidentin! Anfang des Jahres fragte Ursula von der Leyen: Was bedeutet die EU wirklich für unsere Jugend? Besser hätte sie gefragt: Was hat die EU für unsere Jugend getan? Denn darauf gibt es klare Antworten.</p><p lang='de'>In Deutschland sind über ein Viertel aller Kinder von Armut oder sozialer Ausgrenzung bedroht, mehr als im EU-Durchschnitt. In Deutschland erleiden heute fast 6 % der 25- bis 29-Jährigen schwere Entbehrungen, doppelt so viele wie 2019. Damit liegt Deutschland im ärmsten Quartal der 27 EU-Mitgliedstaaten. Nur 73 % aller Deutschen haben einen Sekundarschulabschluss – deutlich unter dem OECD-Durchschnitt von 80 %. Dabei war das deutsche Bildungsbudget 2019 mit fast 230 Milliarden Euro – oder 6,6 % des Bruttosozialprodukts – das höchste der EU.</p><p lang='de'>Doch reichlich fließt das Geld nur für Deutschunterricht für Migranten und die Indoktrinierung der Jugend. So fallen die sprachlichen und mathematischen Fähigkeiten der Grundschüler und 15-Jährigen im internationalen Vorjahresvergleich stetig ab; das gilt für Deutsche gegenüber Europäern und für alle Europäer gegenüber Asiaten. Auch die europäischen Universitäten fallen zurück.</p><p lang='de'>Und trotz massiver öffentlicher Schuldenaufnahme liegt die Jugendarbeitslosigkeit in zahlreichen Regionen Südeuropas immer noch zwischen 35 und 50 %. Dabei haben europäische Frauen heute weniger als 1,5 Lebendgeburten, Frauen in Westafrika indes im Schnitt fünf – selbstverständlich wollen Sie die alle hierherholen.</p><p lang='de'>Fazit: Die Europäische Union versagt auch gegenüber unserer Jugend. Dass Jugendliche nun ab 16 Jahren wählen dürfen sollen und mehr Abgeordnete schon vor ihrem Studienabschluss gewählt werden, ändert daran gar nichts.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="es" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.127" speakername="Jorge Buxadé Villalba" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9654" time="10:46:45" url=""><p lang='es'> – Señora presidente, jóvenes de Europa: Bruselas proclama un Año Europeo de la Juventud, pero os dice que no seréis dueños de nada. Otros han decidido lo que tenéis que hacer, pensar, sentir, vivir o decidir hasta 2030.</p><p lang='es'>Jamás en la historia se había condenado a la juventud a vivir una vida más miserable que la de sus padres. Esforzaos, estudiad, trabajad y no aceptéis las migajas de sus bonos culturales. Es su mundo el que está en ruinas, no el vuestro. Es su agenda la que os impone compartir el coche, la casa o el empleo, no la vuestra. </p><p lang='es'>Sois jóvenes y tenéis todo el derecho a vivir en el peligro y en la temeridad —«no comas carne», «no tomes vino», «no tengas un empleo estable», «no disfrutes de la prosperidad en el lugar donde has nacido»—. Forjad vínculos fuertes: vuestros padres y abuelos. Cultura y tradición. Vuestra historia compartida, que es la nación. Prended fuego a todo lo que es provisional. Audacia y coraje para conquistar lo permanente. </p><p lang='es'>Os acusarán de que sois jóvenes y os dirán que con entusiasmo no se cambian las cosas. </p><p lang='es'>Pero yo os aseguro que, si vuestra ilusión se desborda, sabréis arrastrar a todos aquellos que quieren hipotecar vuestro futuro. </p><p lang='es'>Seguridad en las calles, familias fuertes, empleos estables y una patria que os proteja. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.129" speakername="Leila Chaibi" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9670" time="10:48:09" url=""><p lang='fr'> – Madame la Présidente, attention, Mesdames et Messieurs, roulement de tambour: l’Année européenne de la jeunesse touche à sa fin. </p><p lang='fr'>L’Année européenne de la jeunesse. J’ai fait le test hier soir, je suis allée à Strasbourg et j’ai demandé à tous les jeunes que je croisais s’ils avaient entendu parler de l’Année européenne de la jeunesse. Eh bien, figurez-vous que pas un seul ne m’a répondu oui. Pas un seul.</p><p lang='fr'>Pourtant, ça aurait pu être un événement. Elle avait toutes les raisons d’être, cette Année européenne de la jeunesse. Avec l’explosion du nombre de jeunes obligés de démarrer leur vie active en faisant la queue aux Restos du cœur. Une personne sur cinq qui fait la queue pour l’aide alimentaire a entre 15 et 25 ans – entre 15 et 25 ans! Elle avait du sens, cette Année européenne de la jeunesse, vu le nombre d’étudiants qui naviguent entre bourses et petits boulots et qui sont obligés de se contenter d’un repas par jour parce qu’ils ne peuvent pas payer leurs factures. Pourtant, nous pouvons le dire, aujourd’hui, cette Année européenne de la jeunesse a été une occasion manquée. </p><p lang='fr'>La garantie pour la jeunesse. La garantie pour la jeunesse aurait pu permettre aux jeunes d’accéder à un vrai emploi stable et de qualité. Mais non, finalement, elle les installe dans la précarité. </p><p lang='fr'>Sur le revenu minimum, on attendait une vraie directive contraignante de la Commission européenne, une directive qui donne accès à toutes et à tous au revenu minimum, quel que soit leur âge. Cette directive aurait forcé la France à mettre un terme à la discrimination des jeunes de moins de 25 ans dans l’accès au RSA. Mais non, nous avons eu une recommandation. </p><p lang='fr'>Même les stagiaires. Les stagiaires ont été obligés la semaine dernière de venir devant le Parlement européen pour nous demander l’interdiction de cet esclavage moderne que sont les stages non rémunérés. </p><p lang='fr'>Alors, c’est vrai, j’avoue, j’avais pris goût aux affiches grand format avec des jeunes souriants qui disent «Année européenne de la jeunesse» le matin quand on arrive au Parlement européen. C’est vrai que cela va me manquer. Mais avouez, avouez, on aurait pu faire tellement mieux.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.131" speakername="Clara Ponsatí Obiols" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10111" time="10:50:33" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, we’re concerned about the youth participation and engagement in our European project. Well, what hundreds of Catalan youth are facing right now for their engagement in politics, following their protest, are arrests, trials and prison sentences, police brutality and abuse, and unrelentless infiltration and spying in youth organisations, without – without – judicial oversight. </p><p lang='en'>This is the reality of youth today in Spain, which is in the European Union. Meanwhile, Mr Sánchez’s government is about to pass new laws making repression against dissidents even easier. </p><p lang='en'>Commissioner, colleagues, we say that we need to engage youth in Europe. We have it! Youth are committed to justice and freedom. What we need is that the Commission stops endorsing repression and starts protecting human rights! </p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.133" speakername="Michaela Šojdrová" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8866" time="10:52:01" url=""><p lang='fr'> – Madame la Présidente, bonjour Monsieur le Commissaire, bonjour à tous ceux qui sont jeunes d’âge mais aussi d’esprit.</p><p lang='fr'> – Paní předsedající, Evropským rokem mládeže chceme povzbudit mladé lidi, kteří v době pandemie COVID-19 přišli o mnoho příležitostí. Víme, že mladí lidé nemají rádi formalismus a vědí dobře, že za jeden rok nemůžeme vyřešit všechny jejich problémy. Ale když už tuto příležitost máme, tak ji využijme. Já velmi ráda spolupracuji s mladými lidmi. Potřebuji jejich podněty, <em>feedback</em> a také jejich energii. A chtěla bych v tuto chvíli poděkovat těm, kteří jsou velmi aktivní v rámci <em>Center for European Volunteering</em>, <em>European Youth Forum</em>, českým mladým lidovcům a mladým demokratům, kteří mě zásobují svými podněty, a vím, že se také do letošního roku zapojili. Bylo to např. setkání <em>EPP4Youth</em>, kterého se zúčastnily stovky mladých lidí, a byli nadšeni z té možnosti potkat se se svými vrstevníky. Další akci připravujeme společně s Evropskou komisí a Radou. Bude to 6. prosince závěrečná konference s mladými lidmi, která věřím, že přinese další podněty. </p><p lang='fr'>Z těch, které jsou velmi často zdůrazněny právě mladými lidmi, chci zmínit jeden, který oni považují za velmi důležitý, a to je požadavek mnohem lepší informovanosti o EU v rámci školního vzdělávání. Možná to někoho překvapí, ale je to logické. Mladí vidí svoji budoucnost v Evropské unii a obávají se dezinformací. Ukazuje se, že jednou z cest by mohly být společné projekty učitelských akademií realizované v rámci Erasmus+ nebo Jean Monnet, a Evropský parlament ve svém usnesení žádá Evropskou komisi, aby přijala opatření a umožnila vznik konkrétního vzdělávacího rámce pro evropské občanství. To by byl skutečně hmatatelný výsledek letošního roku mládeže a byl by užitečný i pro mladé v budoucnosti.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="it" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.135" speakername="Massimiliano Smeriglio" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9997" time="10:54:23" url=""><p lang='it'> – Signora Presidente, signor Commissario, onorevoli colleghi, a poche settimane dalla sua conclusione abbiamo la possibilità di confrontarci sull'Anno europeo della gioventù. </p><p lang='it'>Un anno che ha mancato i suoi obiettivi, primo tra tutti quello di raggiungere realmente le giovani generazioni europee, comprendere i loro bisogni, soprattutto dopo la pandemia e nel mezzo dell'attuale crisi sociale.</p><p lang='it'>Vorrei ricordare alla Commissione che siamo ancora in tempo per agire, dando risposte concrete. Innanzitutto implementando lo "EU Youth Test" affinché vi sia un coinvolgimento significativo delle nuove generazioni nel processo decisionale politico. I giovani devono poter avere voce in capitolo quando si decide su politiche che impatteranno sul loro futuro.</p><p lang='it'>È il momento di combattere la precarietà giovanile e dare loro la possibilità di affacciarsi al mondo del lavoro con opportunità di qualità, a partire da un quadro normativo a livello europeo che vieti i tirocini e apprendistati non retribuiti, e su questo aspetto la Commissione e gli Stati membri devono sicuramente fare la loro parte, ma anche il Parlamento deve essere chiaro e unito su questa richiesta. Noi per primi dobbiamo dire basta all'era del lavoro gratuito per poter fare esperienza.</p><p lang='it'>L'educazione crea uguaglianza, ma se il primo passo dopo la laurea è uno stage non retribuito, ci limitiamo a mantenere intatte le disuguaglianze esistenti. La pandemia ha già costretto i giovani a mettere in pausa la loro vita. Il minimo che possiamo fare è garantire loro un inizio del percorso lavorativo senza essere indebitati. Lo dobbiamo a loro, per l'Europa del futuro.</p><p lang='it'>Da ultimo, è per noi fondamentale dare continuità a questo lavoro prolungando l'Anno europeo della gioventù fino al 9 maggio 2023. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="sl" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.137" speakername="Irena Joveva" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9810" time="10:56:27" url=""><p lang='sl'> – Gospa predsednica! Evropsko leto mladih se bliža koncu ali drugače, če želite, evropskega leta mladih še ni konec. To pomeni, da nekako težko danes ugotavljamo njegov končni uspeh oziroma govorimo dovolj podrobno ali konkretno o njegovi zapuščini. </p><p lang='sl'>Namesto tega pa seveda lahko govorimo o konkretnih predlogih izboljšanja življenjskih razmer mladim. Ogromno je področij, ki jih je treba urediti, to vemo vsi, in v minuti jih je nemogoče našteti, je pa mogoče reči, žal, da nam tega letos ni uspelo storiti. Nam je uspelo izpeljati številne dogodke, to seveda drži in to absolutno podpiram, ampak to ni dovolj. In niti ne moremo vsega za nazaj ali za naprej nadomestiti s takšnimi aktivnostmi. </p><p lang='sl'>Na žalost je tako, da mladi nimajo enega krovnega zakona, direktive ali akta, ki bi bil namenjen zgolj njim, zato moramo poskrbeti, da jih vedno postavimo v ospredje. Jaz jih. Z mladimi in za mlade. Najmanj to smo jim dolžni.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.139" speakername="Damian Boeselager" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9629" time="10:57:49" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, Commissioner, colleagues, this week we celebrated the 70th birthday of the European Parliament, which, by the way, is also the average age of a conservative politician in this House. I am obviously joking, but I have to tell it to all of us. We have to be honest. If you listen to the Beatles, the Foo Fighters or Limp Bizkit, you’re not young anymore. If the people that go clubbing over the weekend are half your age, you’re not young anymore. So the reality and the funny thing about an ageing societies is that if you’re older, you outvote the young or, to say it a bit differently, the closer you are to death, the more you decide about the future. This obviously leads to absurd situations where you have a German chancellor, Olaf Scholz, campaigning as a full campaign promise to never touch pension schemes. That’s a great strategy if you want to get the old ones.</p><p lang='en'>A year of youth won’t change these structural issues. And so we have to ask ourselves, what can we actually do? I think what would really help is to actually give voting rights to 16-year-olds and also to ensure that every 18-year-old across this continent has the right to stand as a candidate for elections. We should prioritise the issues that will have a longer-term effect, which means we should not concentrate too much on the short term. The longer-terms are the ones that will actually affect the people who are young now or that are still to be born. That does definitely include the climate.</p><p lang='en'>And then I think as parties, as politicians, we need to make a step, an extra effort, to talk to young people more and to basically show them that it’s more fun to be here to fight against oil and gas than to throw processed food at paintings.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="pt" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.141" speakername="Sandra Pereira" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9922" time="10:59:40" url=""><p lang='pt'> – Senhora Presidente, quando falamos de políticas para a juventude não as podemos desligar de respostas concretas e necessárias para os problemas que os jovens hoje enfrentam. </p><p lang='pt'>É essencial que se ponha fim à exploração e ao flagelo da precariedade. Que haja valorização de salários. Que se garanta aos jovens serviços públicos de qualidade e que não se ignorem as inquietações quanto às discriminações que perduram, e ainda há muitas, e quanto aos perigos para a paz num mundo que é de todos.</p><p lang='pt'>É necessário que os jovens vejam assegurados os seus direitos de acesso ao ensino, à cultura, ao desporto, a uma habitação digna, ao lazer, à saúde e à educação sexual, à igualdade, à participação no movimento associativo. </p><p lang='pt'>É mesmo preciso que a União Europeia e os seus Estados-Membros deixem a propaganda de lado e levem a cabo políticas que possibilitem aos jovens concretizar as suas expetativas, pôr as suas capacidades ao serviço do desenvolvimento e do bem-estar de todos, e que possam transformar os seus sonhos em vida. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.143" speakername="Maria Walsh" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10059" time="11:00:51" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, the objective of our 2022 European Year of Youth was to shine a light on the importance of Europe’s youth in building a better future, and to put them at the centre of decision making. I believe the EU year was successful in some parts in achieving this, but the work cannot stop. It is essential that we, as EU decision makers, continue to welcome young people in every aspect of our work. </p><p lang='en'>We must build a lasting legacy. Yearly youth conferences and events should take place across all four corners of our Union, fostering local debates and encouraging young people to give their much—valued input into developing EU policy. In addition, I ask the Commission to adopt an EU youth test to mainstream a youth perspective into the preparation of all our European policies. </p><p lang='en'>In September, I was delighted to welcome four aspiring parliamentarians from my Midlands–North—West constituency to the Parliament as part of the EPP’s Youth Week. I saw first hand the commitment our young people have to our European peace project, our future and the invaluable perspectives they offered to us all. I want to thank Chloe, Lisa, Amy and Dean for joining us at EPP Youth Week. Let us ensure that we continue to listen to the voices of young people and make their future our ultimate mission. </p><p lang='en'> <em>(The speaker agreed to respond to a blue-card speech under Rule 171(8))</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.145" speakername="Michaela Šojdrová" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8866" time="11:02:39" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>blue-card speech</em> <em>.</em> – Thank you very much, Maria. I know that you are very motivated. You are very hardworking for youth. You mentioned many activities where you participated and actions for youth. But many of our colleagues mentioned that it was late, it was less time for how to raise awareness about a European Year of Youth. </p><p lang='en'>So really, do you share these concerns about awareness of the European Year of Youth? And how can we enhance this awareness of young people and include young people in this decision policy process? </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.147" speakername="Maria Walsh" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10059" time="11:03:26" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>blue-card reply</em> <em>.</em> – Thank you very much for the question, colleague. I do agree with you. I think we rushed it. I think it was a fantastic year. But ultimately, look at the room right now. We should have 705 MEPs talking about how successful the European Year of Youth was in their constituency. We don’t. </p><p lang='en'>We should have younger people as part of this conversation, and not just the younger people sitting up here in the podiums. I think that when we talk about the European youth and protection and this lasting legacy, we also need to deep dive into what worked. I mentioned youth conferences and events, organised local events worked. But, ultimately, who wasn’t in the room? It was all those with different abilities not in the room. It was issues like mental health, like climate change, like the future of digitalisation and their impact on that. Was that heard? It wasn’t. </p><p lang='en'>But now we have time, and ultimately I hope that in this building of a lasting legacy, we do take it seriously, and that in our Culture and Education Committee, as we had agreed, we continue to have youth voices heard because, as I mentioned, it is our mission to protect our peace project for the future. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="es" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.149" speakername="Marcos Ros Sempere" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10112" time="11:04:47" url=""><p lang='es'> – Señora presidenta, comisario, la juventud es el período más determinante de una vida, un momento de florecimiento personal que solo se vive una vez y, como tal, hay que aprovecharlo. De ahí la importancia de este Año Europeo de la Juventud para concienciar sobre ello.</p><p lang='es'>Sin embargo, comisario, ¿cuántos jóvenes han conocido la iniciativa? Lamentablemente, no los suficientes. Hemos fracasado en el objetivo de llegar a la población general. ¿Los motivos? La organización de este año empezó tarde y ha contado con poca financiación y poca implicación.</p><p lang='es'>Pero, aún así, debemos asegurarnos de que el legado de este año vaya más allá, que ayude a los jóvenes a superar los efectos de la pandemia, que los capacite para ser ciudadanos activos y comprometidos, que les informe de todas las oportunidades que ofrece la Unión Europea. La formación constituye un eje central en el desarrollo de nuestros jóvenes y, sin una educación de calidad, inclusiva y sin barreras, tendrán mucho más difícil alcanzar sus metas.</p><p lang='es'>Termino con un momento clave para nuestros jóvenes, la difícil transición al mundo laboral. Es un imperativo democrático que garanticemos una remuneración justa para todos los períodos de prácticas. Es una pena no haber contado con el apoyo de la derecha para defender este derecho tan básico. Por su oposición, no lo hemos podido incluir en la resolución que vamos a votar, pero los jóvenes pueden seguir contando con que los socialistas seguiremos peleando por sus derechos.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.151" speakername="Svenja Hahn" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9778" time="11:06:38" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, dear colleagues, when I entered this Parliament three years ago, I was president of the European Liberals, and in that capacity I had the great honour to travel through 35 European countries. I’ve met many young people from all over Europe. I’ve demonstrated for abortion rights in Poland. I’ve protested against upload filters. I joined the fight against youth unemployment. </p><p lang='en'>All those young people I met had very similar hopes and dreams, filled with expectations for the future. There was always one thing that I heard from them when I was a youth politician, but now also being a parliamentarian: ‘listen to us’. Also, in the Year of Youth, I’ve been to many events, and at every single one of them, I was asked to ensure that this year of the youth will be more than just a show, that it will have a lasting effect, that there will be better processes to include young people. </p><p lang='en'>When I hear the disrespect from the colleagues on the right, from these populists, the disrespect for young people and their involvement, I can just say I am so proud that the Bundestag, the German Parliament, has just approved voting rights for people as of the age of 16. </p><p lang='en'>Young people want to be heard, young people deserve to be heard and, dear Commissioner Breton, you should really listen to young people, especially after the Year of Youth. </p><p lang='en'> <em>(The speaker agreed to respond to a blue-card speech under Rule 171(8))</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="pl" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.153" speakername="Bogdan Rzońca" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9973" time="11:08:40" url=""><p lang='pl'> <em>wystąpienie zasygnalizowane przez podniesienie niebieskiej kartki</em> <em>.</em> – Usłyszałem od Pani o tej aktywności, dużej aktywności Pani wśród młodzieży w ostatnich latach. Chciałbym się Pani zapytać, czy w tej aktywności była też wizyta w takich krajach, gdzie w tej chwili jest największe bezrobocie: Hiszpania, Włochy? Co Pani zrobiła, co Pani proponuje, żeby tę bardzo niekorzystną sytuację, jeśli chodzi o bezrobocie wśród młodych ludzi, zmienić? Co Pani proponuje w swojej aktywności?</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.155" speakername="Svenja Hahn" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9778" time="11:09:28" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>blue-card reply</em> <em>.</em> – I think this is actually an excellent question. We have a different situation of youth unemployment throughout the whole of Europe. Young people have many shared dreams – the first apartment, the first love, and also trying to find a good education, trying to find a job. </p><p lang='en'>The fact is the situation varies throughout the European Union. But also the fact is we have different circumstances. We have governments that make laws that make it harder for young people to get into employment, that favour older colleagues over newer colleagues. We have different education levels and systems in different countries. I come from a country where we have a different education system that also is very training—based. </p><p lang='en'>So I think, especially on fighting youth unemployment, we need to come together to learn from best practice examples to really enable young people into the labour market. Because young people are not just cheap labour; young people are the future. Young people are the hope for better employment. They are the bright ideas of the future. They are the ones that will create jobs in the future. They are the ones that will create new companies in the future.</p><p lang='en'>So it all really comes down to what we bring for education. This is really where I see the Member States in responsibility. On the European level, we can ensure, for example, by being against unpaid internships, by having best practice exchange and knowledge trainings and really bringing young people together, that we also help our Member States to put young people first. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="sl" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.157" speakername="Milan Zver" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8020" time="11:11:08" url=""><p lang='sl'> – Spoštovana gospa predsedujoča, spoštovani gospod komisar, drage kolegice in kolegi! V Evropi živi 74 milijonov mladih od 14 do 29 let. To je relativno veliko. Se splača potruditi zanje, po drugi strani pa v situaciji, ko govorimo o ostarelih družbi v Evropi, premalo. Premalo. </p><p lang='sl'>Toda raziskave kažejo, da mladi želijo biti bolj proaktivni v družbi, hočejo biti bolj vključeni. Opozarjajo na brezposelnost, ki v Evropi še vedno vlada in je močno prisotna v mnogih delih Evropske unije. In prav je, da jim maksimalno pomagamo. In ta pobuda, ki je prišla s strani predsednice Evropske komisije septembra 2021, da imamo naslednje leto evropsko leto mladih, je več kot dobrodošla, ampak prepozna. </p><p lang='sl'>Menim, da so mladinske organizacije in drugi udeleženci imeli premalo časa za dobre priprave in seveda so težave v izvedbi. In tudi za naslednje leto, ko je bilo predlagano tik pred zdajci, da bo to leto veščin, kar je perfektna ideja, zelo dobra, ampak nosi isto slabo točko kot prejšnja pobuda. Preslabo smo usklajeni v evropskih politikah glede dajanja tovrstnih pobud.</p><p lang='sl'>Zato imam dve veliki želji. Prva je ta, da se ta pobuda podaljša za pol leta, da bodo lahko izvedli te svoje projekte, ki so si jih mladi zastavili. In druga pobuda, polagam na dušo Evropski komisiji, da v prihodnje boljše koordinira tovrstne pobude, da se pogovori z nami, ki smo odločevalci v izobraževalnih politikah. Evropska komisija je prvenstveno izvrševalka in bi bilo več kot potrebno, da stopimo skupaj, pogledamo, analiziramo stvari in šele potem sprejmemo zelo pomembne pobude, kot je tudi ta letošnja. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="hr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.159" speakername="Predrag Fred Matić" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9878" time="11:13:16" url=""><p lang='hr'> – Poštovana predsjedavajuća, povjereniče, što su europske institucije konkretno učinile za mlade i koji su opipljivi dugotrajni rezultati cijele ove godine? Ja na to pitanje nemam odgovor, a nisam ga čuo niti od Komisije. </p><p lang='hr'>Tekst koji je pred nama je relativno dobar, ali ostaje činjenica da rezultati neće biti onakvi kakvim smo se nadali. Ono što je mene najviše razočaralo jest činjenica da veliki dio Europljana ni sada ne zna da je ova godina upravo godina mladih i to dovoljno govori o načinu promocije i provedbi aktivnosti koje su, nažalost, ostale na pokušajima nekih zemalja članica, organizacija i pojedinaca, čak i nekih od nas koji smo sami provodili projekte u našim državama. </p><p lang='hr'>U cijelom procesu najviše nedostaju konkretna rješenja i ishodi. Ponovit ću riječi koju sam ovdje izrekao prije gotovo godinu dana. Mladima ne smijemo prodavati floskule poput vi ste naša budućnost, pouzdamo se u vas, na mladima svijet ostaje i slično. A upravo smo to učinili. Iako sam osobno zaista učinio nešto konkretno za mlade tijekom ove godine, sram me je i baš se osjećam kao da sam ih izdao. Kako se osjećaju oni koji nisu učinili baš ništa ne znam, ali sramim se i u njihovo ime. </p><p lang='hr'>Kolegice i kolege, simbolika je lijepa, ali to nije ono što mladi žele i strahujem da smo ih itekako razočarali. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.161" speakername="Monica Semedo" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9987" time="11:14:51" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, 2022 is the Year of European Youth, the year of a generation that went through so many crises recently. I expected the Commission to be more ambitious, to reach those who are less interested in politics. </p><p lang='en'>We, as Renew, organised Renew4Youth – an event that brought together 145 European students, young European students who had fruitful exchanges. They came from the EU but also beyond. This event changed their vision of Europe. </p><p lang='en'>Next year will be the European Year of Skills, and I am proud to be the rapporteur on quality traineeships. Traineeships should be paid. They should occur in better working conditions and trainees should have a real learning experience. </p><p lang='en'>So I say to you colleagues, this is not something we do for ourselves. This is something we do for young Europeans, for the next generation EU. So let’s cooperate on that report, because they deserve it. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.163" speakername="Loránt Vincze" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10046" time="11:16:17" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, Commissioner Breton, by declaring the European Year of Youth, the Commission and the entire European Union made a strong commitment towards young people. I believe this commitment, but also the responsibility of the Union. </p><p lang='en'>I checked the European Year of Youth portal for my constituency. It lists nearly 2 000 events in Romania, but they are not dedicated initiatives and have little to do with the objectives set out by the Commission for the dedicated year. I learned from youth organisations that these activities would have taken place in any case and that they are part of Erasmus+, third—country or other public—entity funded projects. </p><p lang='en'>Imagine that Romania had an allocation of EUR 183 000 for the whole European Year project. The Commission paid just some days ago the first EUR 80 000. Because of this late payment there has actually been no possibility to spend even EUR 1 for the European Year in Romania, when the closing European event is around the corner. This is bad implementation of an otherwise well—intended policy. </p><p lang='en'>Additionally, I learned that for many youth organisations, this year was particularly difficult as the financing through the Erasmus+ programme encountered delays and less organisations received administrative funds. </p><p lang='en'>Colleagues, the message of the youth for us is clear. For them, every year is the European Year of Youth. They should be continuously supported, promoted, asked for advice in youth matters and in European policies, and their organisations given opportunities to have long—term financial stability. We should not deceive them again. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="pt" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.165" speakername="João Albuquerque" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10156" time="11:18:11" url=""><p lang='pt'> – Senhora Presidente, Senhor Comissário, há pouco mais de um mês os socialistas portugueses convidaram 200 jovens a virem ao Parlamento Europeu para expressarem as suas preocupações com o presente e com o futuro. De entre trinta propostas, os jovens elegeram nove prioridades que puderam apresentar à Presidente deste Parlamento: uma estratégia europeia para a saúde mental, transportes públicos europeus gratuitos, acesso à habitação acessível e <em>vouchers</em> gratuitos foram algumas destas prioridades. </p><p lang='pt'>Mas há uma que emergiu inequivocamente como tendo um forte impacto na sua vida e que é o maior obstáculo à sua emancipação: o trabalho não remunerado. </p><p lang='pt'>Senhor Comissário, caras e caros Colegas, sejamos claros: só há uma razão para a proibição dos estágios não remunerados não estar nesta resolução e é a oposição que toda a direita mantém.</p><p lang='pt'>Mais uma vez, quero aqui deixar bem clara a nossa posição e apelar a que se possa avançar neste sentido: é hora de acabar de uma vez por todas com os estágios não remunerados. Em nome destes 200 jovens portugueses e, estou certo, de outros milhares e de todos aqueles que estão na galeria deste Parlamento, esta seria a melhor forma de acabar o Ano Europeu da Juventude e dar um sinal de grande esperança aos jovens europeus. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="ro" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.167" speakername="Vlad-Marius Botoş" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9638" time="11:19:35" url=""><p lang='ro'> – Doamnă președintă, stimate domnule comisar, stimați colegi, Anul European al Tineretului a fost până în acest moment un succes prin implicarea tinerilor din toate statele membre în activități care le-au arătat ce înseamnă Uniunea Europeană și mai ales politicile europene.</p><p lang='ro'>Un lucru foarte important, mai ales în condițiile în care ne confruntăm cu campanii extrem de agresive și, trebuie să recunoaștem, destul de eficiente de decredibilizare a Uniunii Europene ca proiect politic și democratic.</p><p lang='ro'>Acțiunile pe care le facem la nivel european sau finanțarea europeană trebuie să ajungă la mai mulți tineri, să aibă obiective clare și să aibă urmări efective și eficiente în politicile europene. Este nevoie ca acțiunile și politicile europene să fie orientate spre îmbunătățirea condițiilor de viață și de educație ale tuturor tinerilor, indiferent de situația lor materială sau de interesul pe care îl acordă în politică.</p><p lang='ro'>Faptul că mulți dintre cei care au participat la dezbaterile organizate pun pe primul loc educația arată că sunt deschiși și dornici să se dezvolte, să progreseze și este un semnal clar că Uniunea Europeană ar trebui să fie mult mai mult implicată în domeniul educațional.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="hr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.169" speakername="Karlo Ressler" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9953" time="11:20:59" url=""><p lang='hr'> – Poštovana predsjedavajuća, Europska godina mladih opravdano je u fokus stavila mlade koji, nažalost, opet neproporcionalno osjećaju teret krize u kojoj su se našli Europa i svijet. Istodobno, nove generacije pokazuju i dalje da su pokretač razvoja i da posjeduju posebnu snagu, snagu inovacije, snagu kreativnosti, snagu izvrsnosti. </p><p lang='hr'>Zato zaslužuju prije svega sigurnu i mirnu, ali isto tako i održivu i digitalnu europsku budućnost. </p><p lang='hr'>Rat u Ukrajini još je jedan šok za mlade generacije. Umjesto da sjede u učionicama ili treniraju na sportskim terenima, mladi Ukrajinci bili su prisiljeni u svoje ruke uzeti oružje, a to je sudbina koju nitko ne zaslužuje. Zajedno s ostalom europskom mladeži, mladi Ukrajinci zaslužuju sigurnu budućnost, a to su stvari koje danas, nažalost, možda uzimamo olako, zdravo za gotovo, siguran dom, osigurano obrazovanje, siguran posao i obiteljski život. </p><p lang='hr'>Za mlade Europljane rat u Ukrajini, nažalost, još je jedna lekcija i podsjetnik da su to vrijednosti za koje će se i naše generacije morati boriti i morati izboriti. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.171" speakername="Max Orville" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10151" time="11:22:36" url=""><p lang='fr'> – Madame la Présidente, Monsieur le Commissaire, chers collègues, une année pour la jeunesse était une nécessité. Se pose aujourd’hui la question de la continuité de notre action pour nos jeunes. Cette année a souligné combien nos jeunes ont de la ressource et des idées. Enseignant hier, je le voyais tous les jours. Député aujourd’hui, je souhaiterais davantage encourager leur esprit d’initiative et leur créativité.</p><p lang='fr'>Intensifier nos réponses pour améliorer l’insertion, l’éducation pour tous, la lutte contre la précarité ou encore répondre aux problèmes de santé mentale constituent notre priorité. Nous devons partout mieux former nos jeunes et continuer à faire de l’Europe un espace de connaissance. Les garanties européennes pour l’enfance et la jeunesse doivent être plus visibles et assorties d’une communication plus agressive. Nous devons favoriser la mobilité pour nos jeunes, en particulier ceux de nos régions ultrapériphériques, afin qu’ils explorent le monde, d’autres territoires, d’autres cultures et d’autres langues. Erasmus+ est le dispositif le plus pertinent. </p><p lang='fr'>Faire vivre la citoyenneté afin qu’en 2024 nos jeunes votent massivement aux élections européennes et s’impliquent de manière pérenne dans la démocratie européenne. C’est ma feuille de route pour l’héritage de cette Année de la jeunesse afin que chaque jeune sans distinction ait la place qu’il mérite dans notre société. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="sk" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.173" speakername="Peter Pollák" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9937" time="11:24:22" url=""><p lang='sk'> – Vážená pani predsedajúca, chudoba, strach, neistota, aj toto je súčasťou miliónov mladých ľudí v Európe. </p><p lang='sk'>Žijeme náročné časy. Pandémia Covidu-19, ale aj vojna priniesla obavy, strach či pocit izolácie. V Európe, ale aj na Slovensku, v mojej krajine, narastá počet mladých ľudí, ktorí majú extrémistické názory, stretávajú sa s otvorenou agresivitou, dokonca sme nedávno videli, ako mladý človek vraždil na Slovensku z nenávisti. </p><p lang='sk'>O to viac dnes mladí potrebujú našu podporu a pochopenie. Mladých ľudí musíme uistiť, že ich pohľady a názory sú pre nás veľmi dôležité. Mladí Európania musia cítiť našu podporu. Nesmieme podceniť budúcnosť mladých Európanov, pretože oni raz budú tí, ktorí budú rozhodovať o tom, aká Európa bude.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="it" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.175" nospeaker="true" time="11:25:18" url=""><p lang='it'> <em>Procedura "catch the eye"</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="pt" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.177" speakername="Margarida Marques" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9875" time="11:25:36" url=""><p lang='pt'> – Senhora Presidente, eu gostaria de trazer aqui, de continuar, aquilo que o meu Colega João Albuquerque já levantou aqui: o Ano Europeu da Juventude. </p><p lang='pt'>Os anos europeus são anos de compromisso e é de compromisso que temos que falar. E os jovens portugueses pediram os quatro compromissos que falou o meu Colega João Albuquerque, mas pedem também: investir na independência energética através das energias renováveis; promover a reconversão profissional de quem perde o emprego devido à transição digital; a limpeza dos oceanos; a proteção da biodiversidade; a ratificação por parte da União Europeia da Convenção do Conselho da Europa para a Prevenção e Combate à Violência contra as Mulheres e uma estratégia europeia sobre a saúde mental.</p><p lang='pt'>Isto são compromissos, compromissos que os jovens portugueses fazem às Instituições Europeias, e nós, enquanto Parlamento Europeu, temos que ter em conta estes compromissos. Porque os anos europeus só serão um sucesso se, efetivamente, nós nos comprometermos com as ideias, com os projetos, que são partilhados no debate ao longo de todo o Ano Europeu. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="pt" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.179" speakername="Sara Cerdas" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9667" time="11:27:03" url=""><p lang='pt'> – Senhora Presidente, o Ano Europeu da Juventude representou uma oportunidade sem igual de aproximarmos a União Europeia aos jovens. </p><p lang='pt'>Este ano tive a honra de receber no Parlamento Europeu 100 jovens, maioritariamente da Região Autónoma da Madeira, uma região ultraperiférica, para assegurar que estes jovens, que vivem mais longe e enfrentam desafios acrescidos, fazem parte das tomadas de decisão que aqui tomámos para o seu dia a dia. Porque este afastamento da Placa Continental não deve significar um afastamento do projeto europeu e as oportunidades devem ser iguais para todos, quer vivam em São Vicente, quer vivam no centro de Bruxelas. </p><p lang='pt'>Também aqui já foi referido o evento <em>9 for youth</em>, com muitos europeus, entre os quais 200 jovens portugueses que foram trazidos aqui ao Parlamento Europeu, no âmbito desta ação da delegação socialista portuguesa aqui deste Parlamento.</p><p lang='pt'>Que este Ano Europeu não seja de fachada. Tomemos ações em consequência dos seus apelos. São os mais novos os decisores políticos das próximas décadas. E serão eles, os jovens de hoje, que garantirão que este projeto europeu continua. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="it" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.181" nospeaker="true" time="11:28:16" url=""><p lang='it'> <em>(Fine della procedura "catch the eye")</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.183" speakername="Thierry Breton" speakerid="unknown" time="11:28:30" url=""><p lang='fr'> <em>membre de la Commission</em> <em>.</em> – Madame la Présidente, merci à toutes et à tous pour ce débat intéressant, pour le soutien et l’engagement à faire avancer l’agenda européen de la jeunesse. Merci aussi aux très nombreux jeunes qui participent à ces débats et aux moins jeunes qui les accompagnent. </p><p lang='fr'>Un mot pour vous dire que, étant donné que les activités de l’Année ont été mises en œuvre dans un esprit, comme vous le savez, de cocréation – ce qui veut dire que c’est de la collaboration, évidemment, dont il s’agit entre les institutions de l’Union européenne, les parties prenantes, les coordinateurs nationaux et les jeunes –, la définition de l’héritage de l’Année européenne de la jeunesse implique donc également un effort collectif.</p><p lang='fr'>Comme annoncé, la Commission évaluera les résultats et le potentiel des initiatives, proposera des idées pour une approche future plus globale, plus intersectorielle, plus inclusive de la participation des jeunes. En particulier, dans le cadre du suivi de la conférence sur l’avenir de l’Europe, la Commission souhaite associer les jeunes à l’élaboration des politiques au travers de leur participation systémique à des panels de citoyens, ainsi qu’en accordant une attention toute particulière à l’impact des nouvelles politiques sur la jeune génération. </p><p lang='fr'>L’Année européenne de la jeunesse a mobilisé les pouvoirs publics à tous les niveaux – européen, national, régional et local. Grâce aux subventions qui ont été octroyées par la Commission, certains pays, comme par exemple l’Allemagne, l’Irlande ou la Finlande, ont mis en place des subventions de microfinancement accordées à des groupes de jeunes ou à des acteurs du secteur de la jeunesse. </p><p lang='fr'>En ce qui concerne l’appel à prolonger l’Année. Le travail se poursuivra évidemment au delà de 2022 et nous allons continuer à mettre en place des initiatives pour les jeunes et intégrer un volet jeunesse dans les initiatives existantes. Nous allons aussi maintenir la carte des activités sur le portail européen de la jeunesse, ouverte au moins jusqu’à la fin mai 2023, afin que les parties prenantes et les coordinateurs nationaux puissent encore organiser des activités au cours du premier semestre de l’année prochaine. </p><p lang='fr'>De même, on peut dire que la plateforme vocale restera à son tour disponible, permettant aux jeunes de continuer à exprimer leur vision. La Commission, je tiens à le dire ici, se réjouit de l’Année des compétences 2023 pour permettre plus de soutien aux jeunes pour de meilleures formations et les préparer ainsi aux réalités du marché du travail. </p><p lang='fr'>En conclusion, Mesdames et Messieurs les parlementaires, les institutions européennes et les États membres se sont engagés conjointement en faveur de l’Année européenne de la jeunesse 2022 et, on peut dire, l’ont d’une certaine façon créée ensemble. Alors que l’Année touche à sa fin et que nous en faisons le bilan, il s’agira donc d’élaborer, je le redis, tous ensemble un plan sur la manière dont l’héritage de cette Année peut être et doit être perpétué. La Commission se réjouit à l’avance de cette perspective et de poursuivre ainsi notre coopération pour l’avenir de la jeunesse.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="it" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.185" speakername="Pina Picierno" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9135" time="11:32:23" url=""><p lang='it'> Comunico di aver ricevuto una proposta di risoluzione1 conformemente all'articolo 132, paragrafo 2, del regolamento.</p><p lang='it'>La discussione è chiusa.</p><p lang='it'>La votazione si svolgerà oggi giovedì 24 novembre 2022.</p><p lang='it'>_____________________</p><p lang='it'>1 Vedasi processo verbale.</p><p lang='it'> <em> <em>Dichiarazioni scritte (articolo 171)</em> </em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="hu" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.187" speakername="Andrea Bocskor" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9357" time="11:32:23" url=""><p lang='hu'> – Az európai ifjúsági év célja az volt, hogy középpontba helyezze a fiatalokat, különösen a Covid-19 járvány következtében, több és jobb lehetőséget kell nyújtani számukra, és biztosítani, hogy meghallgassák őket, hiszen a fiatalok jelentik Európa jövőjét. Fontosnak tartom a fiatalok aktív szerepvállalását a közéletben, illetve a fiatal nemzedék bevonását a társadalmi vitákba, az ifjúságpolitika alakításába és egyes szakpolitikai döntések meghozatalába, s az is lényeges, hogy a fiatalok hangja az uniós intézményekbe is eljusson. Sajnos az elmúlt időszakban a fiatalok bizalma megingott az Unió intézményeiben, az a kép alakult ki bennük, hogy az EU központi szerveit nem érdeklik a polgárok, lesöprik az asztalról az alulról jövő kezdeményezéseket, példa erre a Minority Safepack esete. A fiatalok, ideológiai harcok helyett a jövőjüket segítő lépéseket várnak el az EU-tól is, főleg a biztonság, az oktatás és munkahelyteremtés területein. A közösségek és értékek szerepe napjainkban különösen felértékelődik. Ebben jelentős szerepet játszanak az ifjúsági szervezetek, és azok közösségépítő és -formáló szerepe. Továbbá nagyon fontosnak tartom, hogy a fiatalok tanulási lehetőségeibe való beruházás nemcsak a fiatalok mint egyének jövőbeli életére van közvetlen hatással, hanem a társadalom egészének gazdasági egészségére és kohéziójára is.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.189" speakername="Victor Negrescu" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8388" time="11:32:23" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>in writing</em> <em>.</em> – 72% of young individuals considered that the most important success factor of the European Year of Youth would be if their demands would be better listened to by decision-makers. For this, we called for EYY outcomes to be mainstreamed across all related EU policies and we proposed to introduce a youth test by which we can measure the impact of all actions and policies on youth and the next generations. Access to quality and inclusive education, developing civic education modules, as well as youth entrepreneurship and environmental education are key points that we must act upon. At the same time, young people from vulnerable categories should be better supported in order for them to have a decent standard of living and more opportunities in regards to education, skills and labour. As S&amp;D rapporteur on the EU budget, we obtained 8 million additional euro for the European Year of Youth in 2022, 123 million euro for Erasmus+ in the 2023 budget and requested financial allocations for the follow-up activities of the EYY. With almost 2000 youth activities organized in Romania, for example, I strongly believe we have to ensure continuity and coherence in our approach so that we can deliver on our commitments towards the young generation.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="it" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.191" nospeaker="true" time="11:32:23" url=""><p lang='it'> <em>(La seduta è sospesa alle 11.32)</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="mt" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.193" nospeaker="true" time="11:32:23" url=""><p lang='mt'> <em>PRESIDENZA: ROBERTA METSOLA </em> <br /> <em>President</em> </p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.194" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="11:32:23" url="">Resumption of the sitting</major-heading>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.196" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:40" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>(The sitting resumed at 12.00)</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="es" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.198" speakername="Margarita de la Pisa Carrión" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10102" time="12:03:02" url=""><p lang='es'> – Señora presidente, señorías, ayer por la tarde acogí un evento de organizaciones de la sociedad civil. Recibimos el boicot por parte de diputados y asistentes. </p><p lang='es'>Esto no responde a la pluralidad que merece ser respetada en esta institución. Damos por supuesto que se tomarán medidas para garantizar la democracia en este espacio. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.200" speakername="Manon Aubry" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9591" time="12:03:34" url=""><p lang='fr'> – Madame la Présidente, je voudrais juste rappeler à nos chers amis de l’extrême droite la raison pour laquelle cet événement a été organisé. C’était une action pacifique qui visait à rappeler une seule chose claire et nette: le droit à l’avortement restera le droit que défendra sans relâche notre institution. Et c’était le sens de notre présence. </p><p lang='fr'>Je voudrais juste rappeler les mots de Simone Veil, qui disait: «Vous devrez rester vigilantes votre vie durant», «il suffira d’une crise politique, économique ou religieuse pour que le droit à l’avortement et les droits des femmes soient remis en cause». Alors sachez, collègues, que vous nous trouverez toujours sur votre chemin quand il s’agira de remettre en cause le droit des femmes.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="es" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.202" speakername="Jorge Buxadé Villalba" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9654" time="12:04:30" url=""><p lang='es'> – Señora presidenta, simplemente, tras oír las palabras de la presidenta del Grupo The Left, o de su representante, quedamos absolutamente liberados para realizar cualquier acto de boicot político a los eventos que se realizan en este Parlamento. </p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.203" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:04:30" url="">Voting time</major-heading>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.205" speakername="Roberta Metsola" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8646" time="12:04:49" url=""><p lang='en'>We will now move to the votes.</p><p lang='en'> <em>(For the results and other details on the vote: see Minutes)</em> </p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.206" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:04:49" url="">Amending Council Regulation (EU, Euratom) 2020/2093 of 17 December 2020 laying down the multiannual financial framework for the years 2021 to 2027 (C9-0386/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.207" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:04:54" url="">Amending Regulation (EU, Euratom) 2018/1046 as regards the establishment of a diversified funding strategy as a general borrowing method (C9-0374/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.208" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:05:18" url="">'Macro-Financial Assistance+' instrument for providing support to Ukraine for 2023 (C9-0373/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.210" speakername="Roberta Metsola" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8646" time="12:05:38" url=""><PARA/><p lang='en'> <em>President. – </em>That is overwhelmingly adopted. This is significant. </p><p lang='en'>Can I also say that this vote is significant not only for the much—needed funding it will make available for the people of Ukraine, but it matters for democracy. </p><p lang='en'>Thank you for showing us, once again, that this Parliament is efficient, is effective, can act and can legislate urgently and fast. This is the democracy and legitimacy of European—level decision making. </p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.211" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:05:38" url="">Non-recognition of Russian travel documents issued in occupied foreign regions (C9-0302/2022 - Juan Fernando López Aguilar) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.212" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:07:05" url="">Establishing the Digital Decade Policy Programme 2030 (A9-0159/2022 - Martina Dlabajová) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.213" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:07:28" url="">Recommendation for a decision not to oppose a delegated act: temporary emergency measures on collateral requirements (B9-0491/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.214" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:07:53" url="">Recommendation for a decision not to oppose a delegated act: value of the clearing threshold for positions held in OTC commodity derivative contracts and other OTC derivative contracts (B9-0490/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.215" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:08:04" url="">The Human rights situation in Afghanistan especially the deterioration of women´s rights and attacks against educational institutions (B9-0501/2022, RC-B9-0506/2022, B9-0506/2022, B9-0522/2022, B9-0524/2022, B9-0525/2022, B9-0526/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.216" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:08:22" url="">The continuing repression of the democratic opposition and civil society in Belarus (RC-B9-0508/2022, B9-0508/2022, B9-0521/2022, B9-0530/2022, B9-0531/2022, B9-0532/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.217" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:10:26" url="">Forced displacement of people as a result of escalating conflict in Eastern Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC) (B9-0500/2022, RC-B9-0507/2022, B9-0507/2022, B9-0523/2022, B9-0527/2022, B9-0528/2022, B9-0529/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.218" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:10:59" url="">The future European Financial Architecture for Development (A9-0270/2022 - Charles Goerens) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.219" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:13:06" url="">Outcome of the modernisation of the Energy Charter Treaty (RC-B9-0498/2022, B9-0498/2022, B9-0502/2022, B9-0510/2022, B9-0513/2022, B9-0536/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.220" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:13:29" url="">Assessment of Hungary's compliance with the rule of law conditions under the Conditionality Regulation and state of play of the Hungarian RRP (B9-0511/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.221" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:16:26" url="">Protection of livestock farming and large carnivores in Europe (RC-B9-0503/2022, B9-0503/2022, B9-0504/2022, B9-0509/2022, B9-0514/2022, B9-0518/2022, B9-0519/2022, B9-0520/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.222" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:18:49" url="">The European Year of Youth 2022 Legacy (B9-0512/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.223" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:25:58" url="">Improving EU regulations on wild and exotic animals to be kept as pets in the European Union through an EU positive list (B9-0489/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.224" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:26:33" url="">Human rights situation in Egypt (B9-0496/2022, B9-0497/2022, RC-B9-0505/2022, B9-0505/2022, B9-0515/2022, B9-0533/2022, B9-0534/2022, B9-0535/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.225" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:26:47" url="">Situation of human rights in the context of the FIFA world cup in Qatar (B9-0539/2022, B9-0541/2022, B9-0542/2022, B9-0543/2022, B9-0537/2022, RC-B9-0538/2022, B9-0538/2022) (vote)</minor-heading>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.227" nospeaker="true" time="12:29:08" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>– Before the vote:</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.229" speakername="Michael Gahler" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8051" time="12:29:24" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, I’m sorry but a brief indication for my colleagues in the EPP. There’s a wrong signal in three amendments. It concerns 36, 43 and 44: please vote minus. Sorry for this intervention. 36, 43, 44: vote minus, please. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.231" speakername="Antonius Manders" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/768" time="12:30:00" url=""><p lang='en'> – Madam President, on Monday, I had a point of order. I want to give a signal and ask the colleagues to stand up and to show a yellow card to FIFA because of their behaviour. If we stand and show our band, then we show that we are against what FIFA is doing in Qatar.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.233" speakername="Roberta Metsola" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8646" time="12:30:18" url=""><p lang='en'>That concludes the vote.</p><p lang='en'> <em>(The sitting was suspended at 12.42)</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.235" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:18" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>VORSITZ: RAINER WIELAND </em> <br /> <em>Vizepräsident</em> </p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.236" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="12:30:18" url="">Resumption of the sitting</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.238" nospeaker="true" time="15:02:26" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>(Die Sitzung wird um 15.02 Uhr wieder aufgenommen.)</em> </p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.239" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:02:26" url="">Request for waiver of immunity</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.241" speakername="Rainer Wieland" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7226" time="15:02:33" url=""><p lang='de'>Die zuständigen ungarischen Behörden haben der Präsidentin einen Antrag auf Aufhebung der parlamentarischen Immunität von Frau Anna Donáth übermittelt. Dieser Antrag wird an den Rechtsausschuss des Parlaments überwiesen.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.242" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:02:33" url="">Approval of the minutes of the previous sitting</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.244" speakername="Rainer Wieland" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7226" time="15:02:42" url=""><p lang='de'>Das Protokoll der gestrigen Sitzung und die angenommenen Texte sind verfügbar. Ich sehe keine Einwände. Damit ist das Protokoll genehmigt.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.245" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:02:42" url="">Revision of the Medical Devices Regulation – how to ensure the availability of medical devices (debate)</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.247" speakername="Rainer Wieland" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7226" time="15:02:51" url=""><p lang='de'>Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgt die Aussprache über die Anfrage zur mündlichen Beantwortung an die Kommission über das Thema „Überarbeitung der Verordnung über Medizinprodukte – wie kann die Verfügbarkeit von Medizinprodukten sichergestellt werden?“ von Angelika Niebler und Peter Liese im Namen der Fraktion der Europäischen Volkspartei (Christdemokraten) (<a href="#reds:iMaQp/O-9-2022-000043" data-rel="reds" redmap-uri="/reds:iMaQp/O-9-2022-000043">O-000043/2022</a> – <a href="#reds:iPlReqo/QOB-9-2022-0030" data-rel="reds" redmap-uri="/reds:iPlReqo/QOB-9-2022-0030">B9-0030/22</a>) ( <a href="#reds:DirContProc/RSP-2022-2960" data-rel="reds" redmap-uri="/reds:DirContProc/RSP-2022-2960">2022/2960(RSP)</a>). </p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.249" speakername="Angelika Niebler" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/6944" time="15:03:11" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Verfasserin</em> <em>.</em> – Herr Präsident, Frau Kommissarin, verehrte Kolleginnen, verehrte Kollegen! Ärzte und Ärztinnen, Krankenhäuser und Hersteller von Medizinprodukten schlagen nun seit über einem Jahr Alarm: Wichtige Medizinprodukte gehen aus, werden nicht mehr hergestellt, werden vom Markt genommen. Beispielsweise Ballonkatheter für Kinderherzen sind derzeit in Europa kaum noch verfügbar, und Kinder mit angeborenem Herzfehler können dann nicht mehr operiert werden.</p><p lang='de'>Was ist passiert? Wir haben 2017 die Neufassung der Medizinprodukte-Verordnung verabschiedet. Ziel war damals, mehr Patientensicherheit zu erreichen. Auslöser für die damalige Überarbeitung der Medizinprodukte-Verordnung war der Brustimplantate-Skandal in Deutschland und Frankreich. Wir wollten mit der Neufassung verschärfte Anforderungen an die Zertifizierung von Medizinprodukten.</p><p lang='de'>Heute müssen wir jedoch leider feststellen, dass zahlreiche Medizinprodukte einfach nicht neu zertifiziert werden, weil der finanzielle und der bürokratische Aufwand gerade bei vielen mittelständischen Medizinprodukteherstellern einfach zu hoch ist; insbesondere gilt das für Nischenprodukte. Daher, glaube ich – mit Blick auf die derzeitige schwierige Versorgungslage mit einigen lebensnotwendigen Medizinprodukten –, muss jetzt dringend etwas passieren. Die Kommission muss endlich einen Vorschlag für eine Änderung der Medizinprodukte-Verordnung vorlegen. Dazu haben wir die Kommission auch schon seit Monaten aufgefordert. Bis jetzt ist – zumindest nach dem, was ich feststelle – nichts passiert, und eigentlich halte ich das für einen Skandal.</p><p lang='de'>Ich möchte deshalb heute drei Fragen an die Kommission richten. Erstens: Wie gedenkt die Kommission dafür Sorge zu tragen, dass Medizinprodukte insbesondere in Krankenhäusern verfügbar bleiben, damit Patienten, die dringend auf diese angewiesen sind, überleben können?</p><p lang='de'>Zweitens: Ich schlage vor, dass bereits erteilte Zertifikate wenigstens so lange gültig bleiben, bis die Prüfung eines Rezertifizierungsantrags abgeschlossen ist. Frage an die Kommission: Ist das eine Überlegung, die geteilt wird?</p><p lang='de'>Und drittens: Erwägt die Kommission, die Medizinprodukte-Verordnung dahingehend zu ändern, dass wenigstens für Nischenprodukte, die bereits unter dem alten Regime zertifiziert wurden, eine Rezertifizierung nicht mehr nötig ist?</p><p lang='de'>Ich bin sehr neugierig, wie die Kommission auf diese drei Anfragen antwortet.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.251" speakername="Stella Kyriakides" speakerid="unknown" time="15:06:01" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>Member of the Commission</em> <em>.</em> – Mr President, honourable Members, first of all I would like to thank honourable Members Niebler and Liese for putting this very important topic on the agenda today. I believe we all agree that patient access to safe medical devices in Europe is essential. And I believe that we also all agree that both access and safety are fundamental priorities in everything we do in this area. </p><p lang='en'>When the European Parliament and the Council adopted the Medical Device Regulation in April 2017, the objective of this was to strengthen quality control and market surveillance. And as MEP Niebler mentioned, we must not forget the breast implant scandal of 2011 that triggered the revision of this legislation. The reasons we had to act as the EU back then for patient safety remain every bit as valid now. </p><p lang='en'>In May 2024, the transitional period of the Medical Device Regulation will be coming to an end. We have made a lot of progress to implement new rules. Some 34 notified bodies have been designated under the regulation. Their capacity has significantly increased compared with the situation under previous EU directives. We have set up expert panels and their secretariat in the European Medicines Agency. They are essential for the more thorough assessment of clinical data. </p><p lang='en'>Yet as we move towards the end of the transition period, it has become extremely clear that ensuring patient access to these devices is not guaranteed. And we are, in fact, facing a serious risk of shortages of medical devices. </p><p lang='en'>Honourable Members, being aware of this risk, we have tasked our experts to take actions and to develop options forward. Aside from continuously monitoring the situation, we are together working with the Medical Device Coordination Group on finding solutions to this problem. A list of mitigation actions was adopted in August in order to increase notified body capacity and to boost preparedness among manufacturers. And several actions are already under way in order to be able to solve the problems that we have seen. </p><p lang='en'>But beyond these efforts, there are calls for additional actions from Members of this House and from several Member States and, of course, from stakeholders. And they include calls for an amendment to the regulation to extend the transition period. We are looking into legislative measures such as amending the regulation to avert the risk of shortages of critical medical devices, and we are already consulting all relevant stakeholders as part of this assessment. </p><p lang='en'>The issues raised in the oral question include the specific situation of so—called orphan devices for small patient groups, which are part of that ongoing assessment. In the meantime, I am pleased to announce and share with Parliament today that the Medical Device Coordination Group has already set up a task force on orphan devices, and has held a workshop with clinicians and industry and other stakeholders. </p><p lang='en'>So what are the concrete next steps for this file? In December, at the occasion of the Health Council, I will be providing the clear proposed solutions to all EU health ministers. My objective is to address both the very short-term issues, but also the structural issues that have appeared. My other objective is the intention to keep this Parliament fully involved in this process. Your support in averting shortages of medical devices is crucial, and I look forward to hearing your views today. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.253" speakername="Peter Liese" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8753" time="15:10:57" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>im Namen der PPE-Fraktion</em> <em>.</em> – Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Die medizinische Versorgung in Europa ist in höchster Gefahr. Das gilt vor allen Dingen für die Versorgung von Kindern.</p><p lang='de'>Ich habe ja früher mal in einer Kinderklinik gearbeitet, und meine ärztlichen Kollegen in der Kinderchirurgie, in der Kinderkardiologie sagen: „Wir sind kurz davor, die Medizin aus den 50er Jahren zu machen, weil moderne Geräte nicht mehr zur Verfügung stehen.“ </p><p lang='de'>Die Gründe sind vielfältig: Brexit, Corona, aber auch, aus meiner Sicht, Mehrheiten im Europäischen Parlament und im Rat, die die gute Sache übertrieben haben, die bei der guten Sache, dem Schutz der Patienten, übers Ziel hinausgeschossen sind. Wir haben damals schon vor zu viel Bürokratie gewarnt. Aber sei's drum; lamentieren nützt nichts. Die Ursachen sind auch ziemlich egal; wir brauchen jetzt eine Lösung.</p><p lang='de'>Ich unterstütze eins zu eins das, was Kollegin Niebler vorgeschlagen hat. Liebe Kommissarin, liebe Stella, wir brauchen diese Schritte schnell, und wir brauchen sie mutig. Meine Fraktion ist bereit, solchen Vorschlägen sehr, sehr zügig zuzustimmen. Und es ist wichtig, dass wir langfristig – gerade bei den Kindern – tragfähige Lösungen finden. Eine <em>Orphan Device Regulation</em> – eine spezielle Regelung, die Anreize für Medizinprodukte bei Kindern zum Beispiel bringt – gibt es in den USA; wir brauchen sie auch in Europa. Der Schutz der empfindlichsten kleinen Patienten muss uns mehr wert sein als bisher.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="es" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.255" speakername="Nicolás González Casares" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9763" time="15:12:47" url=""><p lang='es'> <em>en nombre del Grupo S&amp;D</em> <em>.</em> – Señor presidente, un clínico, con un respirador que dé 12 ventilaciones por minuto y un volumen de respiración de 0,7, lo que quiere es que en un minuto meta 8,4 litros. Esto quiere decir que sea preciso. Y eso es lo que pretendía el Reglamento de productos sanitarios que entró en vigor en 2017, es decir, que no fallaran los productos sanitarios. Ninguno. Y sabemos que hubo casos en que fue así —lo ha mencionado la comisaria—. Hubo, por ejemplo, implantes mamarios que fueron fallidos, prótesis de cadera... Eso sucedió.</p><p lang='es'>Por lo tanto, este Reglamento ha sido un buen marco regulatorio para mejorar la fiabilidad de los productos sanitarios. Creemos que, además, es más transparente y justo. Además, los profesionales sanitarios y médicos así también lo han reconocido. Porque todo lo que queremos es fiabilidad.</p><p lang='es'>Durante la pandemia también trabajamos en el Reglamento de refuerzo de la Agencia Europea del Medicamento, en el que pusimos también elementos que favorecen la disponibilidad de los dispositivos sanitarios, sobre todo en situaciones de crisis. Pero también debemos considerar que tenemos varias herramientas legislativas.</p><p lang='es'>Por supuesto, claro que debemos valorar si, a raíz de la entrada en vigor de este Reglamento, hay algunos casos de productos sanitarios para los que exista un riesgo de escasez, sobre todo en enfermedades raras o en enfermedades pediátricas (en tratamientos pediátricos). Y es posible que sea necesario hacer ciertas derogaciones, como ya se han hecho previamente.</p><p lang='es'>Habrá que estudiarlo caso por caso. Pero no creo que debamos hacer que esta legislación sea más blanda y tengamos menor confianza en aquello que utilizamos para medir o para tratar a los pacientes, para medir sus variables físicas y los tratamientos que aplicamos.</p><p lang='es'>Lo ha mencionado antes Peter Liese: pueden ser otros factores (se ha interrumpido la cadena de suministro, parte de la producción no estaba basada en Europa...). Quizás tengamos que actuar sobre esos factores, localizarlos, ponerles solución y actuar sobre eso. No tanto sobre la legislación.</p><p lang='es'>Por lo tanto, me parece bien que la comisaria, entre otras cosas, haya propuesto estudiar con los Estados miembros qué es lo que está ocurriendo. Pero yo creo que debemos huir de afirmaciones como la de que este Reglamento está haciendo que los pacientes de la Unión Europea reciban una peor atención sanitaria. No creo que sea este Reglamento la causa. Habrá que hacer ajustes, habrá que establecer procedimientos de mejora y habrá que buscar soluciones. Pero lo que necesitamos, sobre todo, es una gran fiabilidad y confiabilidad en los dispositivos sanitarios.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.257" speakername="Véronique Trillet-Lenoir" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10030" time="15:16:10" url=""><p lang='fr'> <em>au nom du groupe Renew</em> <em>.</em> – Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, chers collègues, n’oublions jamais que la proposition de révision de la législation sur les dispositifs médicaux a été publiée suite au drame des prothèses mammaires PIP en 2012. Dix ans plus tard, nous en sommes encore à discuter de la mise en œuvre de cette législation. Cela ne répond pas à notre vision d’une Europe de la santé ambitieuse, pragmatique et surtout indépendante. </p><p lang='fr'>La sécurité des patients ne peut pas être une variable d’ajustement. Les normes sanitaires sont aussi, voire plus, impératives que les autres législations européennes. Nous devons effectivement admettre que la mise en œuvre du règlement est aujourd’hui en danger, de par le trop faible nombre d’organismes notifiés sûrement, mais aussi de par le manque d’anticipation de certains fabricants et la carence de personnels spécialisés.</p><p lang='fr'>C’est vrai, depuis plusieurs mois, tous les acteurs tirent la sonnette d’alarme et il est temps de répondre par des solutions pragmatiques et acceptables pour tous. Alors, d’accord pour adapter la réglementation une nouvelle fois, mais provisoirement et à la marge, pour éviter les ruptures d’approvisionnement potentiellement dangereuses, mais pas pour remettre en cause ce règlement ambitieux et absolument nécessaire à la sécurité des patients européens.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.259" speakername="Tilly Metz" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8258" time="15:18:03" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>on behalf of the Verts/ALE Group</em> <em>.</em> – Mr President, dear all, we have already extended the deadlines for the new rules of the Medical Devices Regulation to apply until May 2024. </p><p lang='en'>The European Parliament was clear that we do not wish another postponement that would be in the disinterest of patients. Now, if the regulation poses issues that will affect access to care for patients, perhaps it really requires other changes to the regulation. So that would be my question to the Commission. What does the Commission recommend? </p><p lang='en'>I would like to stress that Parliament should be involved early on regarding the discussion. I was happy to hear from the Commissioner, who said it is important that the European Parliament is involved in order to discuss possible changes to this regulation instead of having again to face another urgent procedure to extend the deadline to apply the regulation’s rules, which are important. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.261" speakername="Virginie Joron" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9807" time="15:19:20" url=""><p lang='fr'> <em>au nom du groupe ID</em> <em>.</em> – Monsieur le Président, chers collègues, Madame le Commissaire, pendant que le président Macron au forum de l’APEC nous demande dans quel camp nous sommes – Chine ou USA – et déclare que nous avons besoin d’un ordre mondial unique, ou encore qu’au G20 est annoncé le renforcement de la gouvernance mondiale de la santé avec le rôle de chef de file de l’OMS, l’Europe, elle, agonise sous la bureaucratie bruxelloise. La France, elle, enregistre des morts dans ses urgences pour défaut de prise en charge.</p><p lang='fr'>Aujourd’hui, il ne faut pas tomber malade car il n’y a plus de lits d’hospitalisation. Vous avez un cancer? Il faudra attendre que des places se libèrent ou que vous ayez un ami bien placé dans un hôpital. Les forums en jets privés n’auront jamais ces problèmes. Nous aurions en France deux fois moins de scanners par habitant que la Grèce ou le Danemark. Nos hôpitaux français manquent d’infirmières et de scanners. Nous constatons les mêmes défaillances avec ce règlement de 2017 qui a établi un nouveau cadre pour les dispositifs médicaux de diagnostic in vitro, comme les tests de dépistage du VIH, du Covid ou les tests de grossesse. On parle ici de dispositifs médicaux que les hôpitaux de l’Union européenne peuvent conserver, mais il faut savoir que la France de Macron a fermé 4 400 lits d’hôpitaux et suspendu 15 000 personnels soignants pendant la crise Covid. Au lieu de s’améliorer, les soins aux patients se sont dégradés en Europe et en France. À Poissy, cet été, une femme est morte après 28 heures passées aux urgences, sur un brancard.</p><p lang='fr'>On a donc des hôpitaux qui n’arrivent plus à se fournir en dispositifs médicaux, des entreprises européennes noyées dans la bureaucratie et qui doivent arrêter leur production de produits utilisés depuis toujours. Dans tous les domaines, la Commission met en place un système de sociétés privées chargées de certifier les produits. Un marché de 140 milliards d’euros en 2022.</p><p lang='fr'>Mais revenons à notre sujet avec des exemples concrets. Comment expliquer que le certificateur privé allemand TÜV Rheinland puisse encore exercer alors qu’il a été impliqué dans l’affaire des prothèses mammaires PIP? TÜV a certifié ces prothèses avant leur commercialisation, puis réalisé treize contrôles en treize ans sans jamais rien constater. Tout certifier, mais rien vérifier. 400 000 victimes dont 30 000 en France. Dix ans d’attente et de combat juridique. Pour les vaccins Covid, on ne parle pas de 1 000 décès en 30 ans, mais de 11 000 en un an, en Europe, selon les derniers chiffres de l’EMA.</p><p lang='fr'>Autres scandales pharmaceutiques: Pfizer a été condamné à 2,3 milliards de dollars en 2009 pour avoir soumis des fausses déclarations aux autorités pour l’anti-inflammatoire Bextra; Johnson &amp; Johnson, à 775 millions de dollars en 2019 pour avoir minimisé le risque de complications mortelles à cause de son anticoagulant Xarelto.</p><p lang='fr'>Les forums en jets privés oublient cette triste réalité. La déclaration du G20 de Bali diffusée sur le site de la Maison-Blanche a manifestement les réponses à vos questions. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="bg" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.263" speakername="Angel Dzhambazki" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9413" time="15:22:14" url=""><p lang='bg'> <em>от името на групата ECR</em> <em>.</em> – Г-н Председател, г-жо Комисар, колеги, запознавайки се с фактите около преразглеждането на Регламента за медицинските изделия, за пореден път с разочарование се убеждавам, че нещо е дълбоко сбъркано в начина, по който се вземат и прилагат решенията във функционирането на този Европейски съюз. Няма никакво обяснение защо, след като е приет този регламент, поради твърде големите бюрократични и финансови усилия, необходими за повторното сертифициране на набор от медицински изделия, дори тези, които имат отлично качество и се използват дълго време, могат да изчезват неочаквано от пазара, защото дружествата решават да ги изтеглят без всякакво обяснение. </p><p lang='bg'>Резултатът е видим – намаляване на наличността на медицински изделия в цяла Европа, което влошава грижата към пациентите. Доскоро в тази зала всеки беше станал медицински специалист, разбираше от пандемии, обсъждаше китайския вирус, какво било, какво не било, как се изтощавали медицинските грижи, липса на лекарства, липса на вентилатори и така нататък, и така нататък. Изглежда обаче, че това е минало като обяснение, всички са го забравили и сега отново се повтарят едни и същи грешки. Необяснимо е това поведение и е необяснимо лишаването на гражданите на държавите – членки на Европейския съюз от адекватна, навременна и необходима за тях медицинска грижа. </p><p lang='bg'>Г-жо Комисар, време е Европейската комисия да започне да действа адекватно, да си гледа работата. Това е във ваш интерес, не в наш. Ние често ви критикуваме за тези неща, но не е лошо да вземете да прекратите тази порочна практика на законодателство, което засяга интересите на гражданите на държавите членки.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="fr" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.265" speakername="Anne Sander" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7879" time="15:23:52" url=""><p lang='fr'> – Monsieur le Président, Madame la Commissaire, chers collègues, nos hôpitaux et soignants portent sur leurs épaules une pression très forte et, aujourd’hui, une nouvelle difficulté s’ajoute à cela concernant l’approvisionnement de matériel médical. Les respirateurs, les défibrillateurs, les prothèses et bien d’autres dispositifs encore, essentiels à la santé de tous, risquent de manquer, avec tout ce que cela implique en termes de prise en charge des patients. </p><p lang='fr'>Les entreprises du secteur et notre Parlement ont, à plusieurs reprises déjà, alerté la Commission européenne au cours des dernières années. En plus de la situation économique actuelle, ces entreprises se voient imposer des contraintes administratives lourdes et parfois, aujourd’hui en tout cas, impossibles à remplir faute d’organismes de certification en nombre suffisant. Ces entreprises ont aujourd’hui besoin de sécurité. Alors, nous nous tournons vers la Commission européenne à qui nous demandons de trouver rapidement des solutions concrètes.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.267" speakername="Vlad-Marius Botoş" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9638" time="15:25:08" url=""><p lang='de'> – Herr Präsident, Frau Kommissarin, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Unser Ziel von allen am Gesetzgebungsprozess Beteiligten ist es, den Rechtsrahmen für ein sicheres und leichteres Leben der europäischen Bürgerinnen und Bürger zu gewährleisten. Dies war – davon bin ich überzeugt – auch der Sinn und Zweck der Revision der Medizinprodukte-Verordnung. Jedoch sehen sich Patienten und Anbieter von Nischenprodukten größeren Anforderungen als zuvor gegenübergestellt, vor Schwierigkeiten gestellt, für deren Lösung sie spezielle Mittel bereitstellen müssen, was hohe Kosten für Patienten oder Gesundheitssysteme in den Mitgliedstaaten bedeutet.</p><p lang='de'>Ich verstehe das Ziel, die Patienten besser zu schützen, aber wir müssen die tatsächlichen Auswirkungen der Umsetzung der Vorschriften beobachten und schnell Änderungen vornehmen, damit Patienten gleichen Zugang wie zuvor zu den von ihnen benötigten Medizinprodukten haben, ohne mehr zu bezahlen. Wir müssen den Markt genau beobachten, um alle auftretenden Probleme zu erkennen und sehr schnell die Korrekturen zu finden, die die Patienten benötigen.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.269" speakername="Michael Bloss" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9628" time="15:26:31" url=""><p lang='de'> – Herr Präsident, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen, Frau Kommissarin! Wir wollen eine Transformation hin zu Nachhaltigkeit, und wir wollen sichere Medizinprodukte. Aber mich erreichen aus meinem Wahlkreis viele Hilferufe von Unternehmen: Spezialisierte Produkte, wie Skalpelle für Kinder mit wenigen Auflagen und oft gefertigt von kleinen Unternehmen, werden mit Massenprodukten von multinationalen Unternehmen in einen Topf geworfen. Die Hersteller ziehen dann die Produkte vom Markt, weil sie die Auflagen nicht erfüllen können, und das können wir nicht wollen.</p><p lang='de'>Wir laufen in einen immensen Flaschenhals zu. Bis Mai 2024 laufen bis zu 24 000 Zertifikate aus, aber durch die benannten Stellen können jährlich nur 6 300 Zertifikate ausgestellt werden. Wir müssen verhindern, dass es hier zu Engpässen kommt und lebensrettende Produkte vom Markt genommen werden.</p><p lang='de'>Klar ist: Der jetzige Zustand ist nicht zufriedenstellend. Wir brauchen jetzt schnelle Lösungen für die Gesundheit, aber mittelfristig muss die Verordnung auf belastbare Füße gestellt werden, sodass sich dieses Drama nicht alle paar Jahre wiederholt.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.271" speakername="Deirdre Clune" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9163" time="15:27:55" url=""><p lang='en'> – Mr President, colleagues, I absolutely want to see the full and effective application of the Medical Device Regulation, because it is extremely important for patients and for those providing their medical care to give assurance on the safety and the effectiveness of these devices. </p><p lang='en'>But I do not want to see a situation develop whereby there will be a shortage – or, as some fear, an unavailability – of vital products. Doctors say that they are already struggling with shortages and they are fearful that this situation will become much more serious. </p><p lang='en'>The slow implementation of the medical device legislation and the limited capacity of notified bodies has led to this situation. Without urgent action, this situation will only get worse and these shortages will impact on patients and on the healthcare system. </p><p lang='en'>So, Commissioner, I welcome your statement today that in December you’re going to bring forward clear proposals to address this situation. I would hope that this will include proposals for a targeted legislative solution that will protect those devices that are already on the market. What we need, as well, is a targeted or tailored transition period for some devices. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.273" nospeaker="true" time="15:28:53" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Spontane Wortmeldungen</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.275" speakername="Seán Kelly" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8784" time="15:29:11" url=""><p lang='en'> – A Uachtaráin, Ireland has urgent and significant concerns regarding the Medical Devices and In Vitro Diagnostics Regulations. There are real issues with the implementation of the directive that need to be addressed. </p><p lang='en'>The regulations introduce new certification requirements. However, substantial and immediate certification bottlenecks mean that Ireland could face considerable shortages in key medical products in the near future. This places patients’ lives at risk and our healthcare system under strain. </p><p lang='en'>If these bottlenecks are not addressed by the May 2024 deadline for certification, there is a risk that one in four med—tech products currently in use could be discontinued. At a time when Europe should be building up homegrown industry and investing in innovation, without some adjustments to the implementation of this regulation we risk losing med—tech firms to the US and other markets outside the EU, and thus losing out on investment and competitiveness in this area. </p><p lang='en'>The Irish Government is calling for a legislative proposal to prevent the loss of existing safe and essential med—tech products.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="lt" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.277" speakername="Juozas Olekas" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9909" time="15:30:32" url=""><p lang='lt'> – Gerbiamas Pirmininke, gerbiama Komisijos nare, iš tikrųjų, jeigu norime suteikti gerą pagalbą savo pacientams, mes turime turėti tris dalykus: specialistus, priemones ir pacientų pasitikėjimą. Šiandien kalbame apie priemones, kurias galime panaudoti gydant pacientus. Aš norėčiau paraginti Komisiją nemažinti kokybės reikalavimų, bet sumažinti biurokratiją, kuri šiandien slegia mūsų medicinos priemonių gamintojus ir kartais neleidžia užtikrinti reikiamos kokybės ir priemonių kiekio. Aš kviesčiau, kad mes visi bendromis pastangomis pabandytume, sumažinę biurokratiją, įgyvendinti gamybos pakilimą Europos Sąjungoje ir taip užtikrinti pacientams ir gydytojams reikiamą medicinos prietaisų kiekį, bet tuo pačiu iš tikrųjų sumažinti biurokratiją, kuri slegia, ir tokiu būdu, neatidėliojant savo sprendimų tolimesniam įgyvendinimui, jau 2024 m. turėti pasikeitusią situaciją. </p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.279" speakername="Andreas Schwab" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7693" time="15:31:57" url=""><p lang='de'> – Herr Präsident, Frau Kommissarin! Auf Twitter weist der Europäische Ärzteverband heute darauf hin, dass er dringend darum bittet: </p><p lang='de'>‘European doctors aim to ensure the availability of medical devices.’</p><p lang='de'>Das ist ein Warnsignal, das wir nicht mit der sonst üblichen technischen Ruhe hier zur Kenntnis nehmen können. Wenn kleine Kinder nicht mehr behandelt werden können, weil die dafür notwendigen Gegenstände nicht mehr zur Verfügung stehen, weil es an den Genehmigungsverfahren Engpässe gibt, dann kann uns das nicht kalt lassen. Das ist zunächst einmal eine Katastrophe für die betroffenen Patientinnen und Patienten, aber es ist natürlich auch wirtschaftlich ein Problem, weil der Zulassungsprozess inzwischen in den USA schneller geht als bei uns.</p><p lang='de'>Und deswegen, Frau Kommissarin Kyriakides: Hier ist <em>political leadership</em> gefordert. Es reicht nicht zu sagen, es wird dort und hier was gemacht. Sie müssen die politische Verantwortung dafür übernehmen, dass an dieser Stelle jetzt etwas vorwärts geht. Denn wenn wir jetzt nicht handeln, verlieren wir in zwei Jahren über 20 000 zertifizierte Produkte. Und das können wir uns im Interesse der Patientinnen und Patienten nicht erlauben, aber wir können es uns auch nicht erlauben, weil unsere Wirtschaft davon lebt.</p><p lang='de'>Deswegen: Bitte werden Sie persönlich jetzt tätig.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.281" nospeaker="true" time="15:33:10" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>(Ende der spontanen Wortmeldungen)</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.283" speakername="Stella Kyriakides" speakerid="unknown" time="15:33:26" url=""><p lang='en'> <em>Member of the Commission</em> <em>.</em> – Mr President, honourable Members, first of all, thank you for bringing this important file for discussion in the European Parliament. And I have said already that this is a priority for us, for the European Commission. And our intention is not, as has been heard, to hurt the citizens, but to protect them. So quality is paramount. And I can assure you that it is a political priority for the Commission and for myself, because we are fully aware of the challenges, and we have wasted no time. </p><p lang='en'>Now, the data received from the notified bodies and industry show that the situation is indeed extremely challenging. Only around 2 000 certificates have been issued under the Medical Device Regulation, while about 23 000 will be expiring in May 2024. This is why the Medical Device Coordination Group has been working on a list of actions, and all stakeholders are involved, including the medical associations, in order to look at what we can change. And we expect that the important actions that we will take will make a real difference. </p><p lang='en'>We are also, as a Commission, listening carefully to all calls for additional measures, including an amendment of the Medical Device Regulation. And we are proceeding with the next steps. </p><p lang='en'>Now, I don’t think there is anyone in this plenary who will say that the unavailability of medical devices needed for health systems and patients isn’t extremely worrying. And this is a priority. But the Medical Device Regulation allows Member States to grant at national level derogations from the applicable conformity assessment procedures. And in some Member States they are able to apply these to bridge the gap between the expiry of an old certificate and the issue of a certificate under the MDR. </p><p lang='en'>The Medical Device Coordination Group is now working to find a uniform approach for these measures. However, we fully recognise that as more certificates expire, the worse the situation is expected to become. So we’re very conscious of the urgency that I have heard spoken in this plenary in order to avoid shortages of medical devices, which will put patient safety at risk. </p><p lang='en'>The regulations on medical devices are a very important step towards providing safe and better performing devices, and these are to benefit the patients and health. As I’ve said, we’re working on a legislative proposal plus other actions. Our task is to ensure that safe devices – and this needs to remain a priority – remain available for patients and for our health systems. </p><p lang='en'>So let me assure you that I will be remaining in very close contact with this House over the next few weeks and will keep you fully informed of our next steps.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.285" speakername="Rainer Wieland" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7226" time="15:37:02" url=""><p lang='de'>Die Aussprache ist damit geschlossen.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.286" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:37:02" url="">Explanations of vote</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.288" speakername="Rainer Wieland" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7226" time="15:37:13" url=""><p lang='de'>Als nächster Punkt der Tagesordnung folgen die Erklärungen zur Abstimmung.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.289" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:37:13" url="">'Macro-Financial Assistance+' instrument for providing support to Ukraine for 2023 (C9-0373/2022)</minor-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.291" nospeaker="true" time="15:37:21" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Mündliche Stimmerklärungen</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="bg" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.293" speakername="Angel Dzhambazki" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9413" time="15:37:38" url=""><p lang='bg'> – Г-н Председател, гласувах в подкрепа на този доклад. Неотдавнашната ескалация на бруталната военна агресия, прощавайте много, на Русия срещу Украйна, е потвърждение за нейното решение да нарушава основните права на Украйна на независимост, суверенитет и териториална цялост в рамките на международно признатите й граници и да унищожи жизнеспособността й като държава. </p><p lang='bg'>Смелостта, куражът и решимостта на украинския народ да защитава страната си заслужават дълбоко уважение и благодарност. Чрез подхода „Екип Европа“ Европейският съюз, неговите държави членки и европейските финансови институции мобилизираха в началото на руската военна агресия 19 милиарда евро за икономическа, социална и финансова издръжливост на Украйна. Това, съчетано с подкрепата от бюджета на Съюза – 12,4 милиарда евро, включително макрофинансовата помощ в подкрепа на Европейската инвестиционна банка, Европейската банка за възстановяване и развитие, изцяло и частично е гарантирано от бюджета на Европейския съюз, както и допълнителната финансова подкрепа от държавите членки в размер на 7,3 милиарда евро. Това би трябвало да бъде част от нашето задължение да подкрепим нападнатата държава, за да може тя да устои на агресията.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.294" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:37:38" url="">Establishing the Digital Decade Policy Programme 2030 (A9-0159/2022 - Martina Dlabajová)</minor-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.296" nospeaker="true" time="15:38:55" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Mündliche Stimmerklärungen</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.298" speakername="Seán Kelly" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8784" time="15:39:01" url=""><p lang='en'> – A Uachtaráin, the Digital Decade Policy Programme is a key step towards the EU achieving its objectives for the digital transformation of society and the economy. The path to a Digital Decade Programme reinforces the EU’s position as a digital leader and promotes human—centred, inclusive and sustainable digital policies. </p><p lang='en'>The past number of decades has seen significant developments in the internet, the digital economy and electronics, and the Digital Decade Policy Programme will ensure the EU achieves its aims for an inclusive and sustainable digital transformation. </p><p lang='en'>This programme ensures that at least 20 million ICT specialists are employed in the EU by promoting the access of women to this field. The programme will also ensure more than 90% of SMEs in the EU will reach at least a basic level of digital integration. </p><p lang='en'>I am therefore pleased to support the path to a digital decade.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.299" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:39:01" url="">The future European Financial Architecture for Development (A9-0270/2022 - Charles Goerens)</minor-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.301" nospeaker="true" time="15:40:19" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Mündliche Stimmerklärungen</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="ga" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.303" speakername="Seán Kelly" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8784" time="15:40:22" url=""><p lang='ga'> – A Uachtaráin, táim sásta an moladh seo d’fhorbairt Ollstruchtúir Airgeadais Eorpaigh a thacú. Beidh ról ríthábhachtach aige ag deimhniú go dtroidfidh an tAontas Eorpach i gcoinne bochtaineachta agus éagothroime. Cinnteoidh sé go n—oibreofar i dtreo spriocanna forbartha iar-bhunaithe na Náisiún Aontaithe agus go stopfar athrú aeráide na cruinne. Deimhneoidh an plean seo go n-oibreoidh tíortha an Aontais Eorpaigh agus na hinstitiúidí le chéile chun comhtháthú polasaí a bhaint amach. Ina theannta sin, cinnteoidh sé go mbainfear úsáid éifeachtach as airgead poiblí. Tagróidh an plean seo d’fhorbairt pholasaí an Aontais Eorpaigh i ndiaidh na paindéime agus i ndiaidh iarmhairtí chogadh na hÚcráine. Feabhsóidh forbairt Ollstruchtúir Airgeadais Eorpaigh léargas an Aontais agus an tionchar atá ag an Aontas ar an domhan airgeadais.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.304" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:40:22" url="">Outcome of the modernisation of the Energy Charter Treaty (RC-B9-0498/2022, B9-0498/2022, B9-0502/2022, B9-0510/2022, B9-0513/2022, B9-0536/2022)</minor-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.306" nospeaker="true" time="15:41:49" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Mündliche Stimmerklärungen</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="en" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.308" speakername="Seán Kelly" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/8784" time="15:41:53" url=""><p lang='en'> – <em>A Uachtaráin</em>, the Energy Charter Treaty plays a key role in energy policy across Europe. However, in the absence of any substantial update of the ECT since the 1990s, it is clear that the modernisation of the Treaty is due. I welcome efforts by the EU and its Member States to drive the modernisation process of the Energy Charter Treaty, particularly on investment protection standards and the fostering of sustainable development. </p><p lang='en'>I also welcome the position to end protections granted to investments in economic activities considered to be significantly harmful and that undermine the EU’s climate objectives. It is clear the Energy Charter Treaty is in need of reform, particularly given the current energy crisis and the fight against climate change. </p><p lang='en'>I therefore call on the European Commission and EU Member States party to the ECT to support its modernisation and to ratify the modernised treaty. </p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.309" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:41:53" url="">Assessment of Hungary's compliance with the rule of law conditions under the Conditionality Regulation and state of play of the Hungarian RRP (B9-0511/2022)</minor-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.311" nospeaker="true" time="15:43:16" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Mündliche Stimmerklärungen</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="bg" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.313" speakername="Angel Dzhambazki" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9413" time="15:43:23" url=""><p lang='bg'> – Г-н Председател, гласувах против този доклад категорично, защото мерките съгласно Регламента относно обвързаността с условия на живот трябва да бъдат прилагани от Комисията, която нарушава принципите на правовата държава и пряко засяга или има сериозна опасност да засегне доброто финансово управление на Съюза. По никакъв начин тази политика, която се води от Европейския съюз и Европейския парламент по отношение на Унгария, за спиране на 65 % от бюджетните кредити за поети задължения в рамките на политиката на сближаване не отговаря на действителността и на никаква логика на Европейския съюз, на идеята за върховенство на закона. </p><p lang='bg'>Темата „върховенство на закона“ се използва, за да бъдат налагани политики в редица държави членки, между които и Унгария. Това е абсолютно неприемливо и недопустимо, противоречи на характера на Договорите и противоречи на идеята за Европейски съюз. По тази причина такъв подход на изнудване, на извиване на ръце не може да бъде подкрепен по никакъв начин, защото именно в тези подходи се крие и засилващата се роля на скептицизъм на много граждани на държави - членки на Европейския съюз.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.314" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:43:23" url="">Protection of livestock farming and large carnivores in Europe (RC-B9-0503/2022, B9-0503/2022, B9-0504/2022, B9-0509/2022, B9-0514/2022, B9-0518/2022, B9-0519/2022, B9-0520/2022)</minor-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.316" nospeaker="true" time="15:44:40" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Mündliche Stimmerklärungen</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="bg" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.318" speakername="Angel Dzhambazki" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/9413" time="15:44:44" url=""><p lang='bg'> – Г-н Председател, гласувах в подкрепа на този доклад, защото нарастващите популации на вълка в Европейския съюз и проблемът, който уж тези популации създават по отношение на биоразнообразието и традиционното животновъдство в Европа, както и необходимостта от съвместна оценка на консервационния статус и трансграничните мерки за опазване и управление на популацията на едрите хищници по научно обоснован начин, съответстват на екологичните изисквания за видовете вълци, които обитават обширни райони и извършват големи миграции. По тази причина ловът трябва да се разреши, в рамките на добрата практика, на правилата и начина, по който работят тези ловни дружинки, за да могат те да извършват полезната дейност, с която да защитават стопанството и да защитават човешки животи и стопанството на хората. </p><p lang='bg'>България дава положителен пример за това как в държава с най-малко инвестиции в Европа по отношение на лова на вълци, ареалът и числеността на този хищник се увеличава, въпреки мерките. От друга страна, мечката като строго защитен вид у нас през последните 10 години, намалява с повече от 30% по официални данни.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.319" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:44:44" url="">The European Year of Youth 2022 Legacy (B9-0512/2022)</minor-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.321" nospeaker="true" time="15:46:03" url=""><p lang='de'> <em>Mündliche Stimmerklärungen</em> </p></speech>
        <speech lang="ro" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.323" speakername="Eugen Tomac" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/10024" time="15:46:16" url=""><p lang='ro'> – Domnule președinte, am susținut această rezoluție, se apropie deja de final acest An al Tineretului European.</p><p lang='ro'>S-a discutat inclusiv în acest plen despre viitorul tinerilor din Europa, în cadrul Conferinței privind viitorul Europei, însă cred că facem prea puțin pentru tranziția de la școală spre câmpul de muncă și avem nevoie de instrumente mult mai puternice pentru a-i putea susține pe tinerii care astăzi sunt profund afectați de toate transformările.</p><p lang='ro'>Am trecut de la criza de sănătate publică la o nouă criză care privează tinerii de foarte multe oportunități și cred că Comisia are obligația să vegheze ca statele membre să implementeze garanția pentru copil și garanția pentru tineret, mecanisme prin care putem oferi noi soluții practice, astfel încât tinerii să se simtă mult mai bine integrați și protejați în societatea europeană.</p></speech>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.325" speakername="Rainer Wieland" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7226" time="15:47:20" url=""><p lang='de'>Damit ist dieser Tagesordnungspunkt geschlossen.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.326" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:47:20" url="">Approval of the minutes of the sitting and forwarding of texts adopted</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.328" speakername="Rainer Wieland" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7226" time="15:47:31" url=""><p lang='de'>Das Protokoll dieser Sitzung wird dem Parlament zu Beginn der nächsten Tagung zur Genehmigung vorgelegt.</p><p lang='de'>Wenn es keine Einwände gibt, werde ich die in der heutigen Sitzung angenommenen Entschließungen den in diesen Entschließungen genannten Personen und Gremien übermitteln.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.329" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:47:31" url="">Dates of forthcoming sittings</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.331" speakername="Rainer Wieland" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7226" time="15:47:47" url=""><p lang='de'>Die nächste Tagung findet vom 12. bis zum 15. Dezember statt.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.332" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:47:47" url="">Closure of the sitting</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.334" speakername="Rainer Wieland" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7226" time="15:47:58" url=""><p lang='de'>Meine Damen und Herren, liebe Kolleginnen und Kollegen! Ich bedanke mich sehr für das Mittun in dieser Woche. Ich bedanke mich bei den Diensten sehr herzlich für ihre Arbeit, bei den Dolmetschern, bei den Saaldienern, bei der GD PRES.</p><p lang='de'>Wenn Sie rauskommen, dann sehen Sie, dass der Straßburger Christbaum schon bereitsteht. Wir haben die längst mögliche Adventszeit; am kommenden Sonntag ist 1. Advent. Der Christbaum steht bereit, er wird jetzt noch geschmückt, und morgen wird der Straßburger Weihnachtsmarkt eröffnet.</p><p lang='de'>Ich wünsche Ihnen eine gute und gesunde Nachhausereise und einen frohen Beginn der Adentszeit.</p><p lang='de'> <em>(Die Sitzung wird um 15.48 Uhr geschlossen.)</em> </p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.335" nospeaker="true" lang="en" time="15:47:58" url="">Adjournment of the session</major-heading>
        <speech lang="de" id="com.kildarestreet.eu/europarl/2022-11-24a.337" speakername="Rainer Wieland" speakerid="eu.europarl/member/7226" time="15:48:30" url=""><p lang='de'>Ich erkläre die Sitzungsperiode des Europäischen Parlaments für unterbrochen.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>